<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Prahlad Yeri's Blog - Android</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/android.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2020-09-05T12:15:00+05:30</updated><subtitle>Educate and solve problems is my mantra. I'm skilled in web development and a quick learner, I also like blogging and contributing to open source.</subtitle><entry><title>How to clear individual site cookies on android firefox</title><link href="/blog/2020/09/how-to-clear-individual-site-cookies-on-android-firefox.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-05T12:15:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-09-05T12:15:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-09-05:/blog/2020/09/how-to-clear-individual-site-cookies-on-android-firefox.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One might wonder why an entire blog post is needed for a simple matter of clearing cookies on a web browser in the 21st century. But believe it or not, such are the state of things when it comes to android browsing! Firefox is a great browser to have on …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One might wonder why an entire blog post is needed for a simple matter of clearing cookies on a web browser in the 21st century. But believe it or not, such are the state of things when it comes to android browsing! Firefox is a great browser to have on Android because it gives you three features which are impossible to get even with Google's Chrome:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plugin Support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ad Blocking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Privacy &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's why over 3 million users have decided to stick with firefox despite the fact that its performance totally lacks in comparison to Chrome. Even so, there are some annoying bugs in firefox such as not being able to clear cookies for individual websites (at least as of version 68.11). This seemingly simple feature isn't available out of the box on firefox and when I googled for it, I found two solutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this &lt;a href="https://android.stackexchange.com/a/120476/38760"&gt;android stackexchange answer&lt;/a&gt; suggests, you can try extracting the below data file (where firefox stores cookies) to your PC, edit it and then put it back (you must be rooted though):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;/data/data/org.mozilla.firefox/files/mozilla/{YOUR_PROFILE}/cookies.sqlite
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you aren't rooted or you don't want to go through the above troubled exercise, I've found a much simpler solution which is to install &lt;a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/a-cookie-manager"&gt;this extension called Cookie Manager by Rob W&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the android firefox browser supports extensions, I found it much easier to just install this extension, open it and type a domain such as *.reddit.com for which you want the cookies deleted, and press the "Search cookies" button:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="cookie manager" src="/uploads/cookie_manager.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you just click the "Select all" button at the bottom followed by "Remove selected", that's it!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Android"></category><category term="Firefox"></category></entry><entry><title>How to Unbrick and revive a totally lifeless Xiaomi Mi-Pad</title><link href="/blog/2016/07/how-to-unbrick-lifeless-xiaomi-mi-pad.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-13T04:21:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-07-13T04:21:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-07-13:/blog/2016/07/how-to-unbrick-lifeless-xiaomi-mi-pad.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, my brand new Xiaomi Mi-Pad arrived via Flipkart and no sooner did I have it in my hands, I started installing useful apps like Greenify, ES File Explorer, etc. Two days went by and I was disappointed to learn that it doesn’t support a USB Dongle (Data …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, my brand new Xiaomi Mi-Pad arrived via Flipkart and no sooner did I have it in my hands, I started installing useful apps like Greenify, ES File Explorer, etc. Two days went by and I was disappointed to learn that it doesn’t support a USB Dongle (Data Card) which is a very common method of Internet access in India. The only way I could have it was to root the tablet. And it was while rooting using SuperSU app that I foolishly selected a wrong click and ended up bricking my brand new tablet.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a &lt;em&gt;hard brick&lt;/em&gt;, meaning my tablet showed no signs of life when switched on or connected to a PC through a USB cable. Had it been a &lt;em&gt;soft brick&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that I were able to boot to MIUI Recovery by pressing Power+UpVolume or to FastBoot Recovery by pressing Power+DnVolume button, it would have been easy to recover. But my tablet was totally dead. Even after charging for next 6 hours, all it did was light up a black LED screen for a second or two and then vanished for any combination of those buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem was that the wrong click that I made had caused the tablet bootloader to be corrupted. And in the android world, if the bootloader is lost, then your device is literally as useful as a brick! Unlike 8086 PCs, android tablets don’t have a hard-wired BIOS to recover things from, the bootloader is as good as the BIOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now obviously, I was disappointed and annoyed. After spending ₹10,999 on a brand new tablet, this was not what I was hoping for. Getting service from a Xiaomi service center was not an option as they are very rare in India. Besides, OEMs hardly provide warranty/support to people who try and root their devices, do they? So naturally, I had to myself find a way out of this. My research finally led me to a post by a Russian hacker who had successfully revived the tablet from this very situation. In this article, I’ll note down exactly what steps I had taken to revive it and hope that someone might find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the solution is easy and straight-forward, there are some tricky areas where you might run into trouble. If you don’t have the confidence to open up an electronic device using a screwdriver or flash a stock ROM, just say quits and if possible, ask help from someone you know who is used to do it. Basically, the process involves this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the back-cover by separating it from the screen (fingernails or a sharp object will do) and unscrew the plastic panel that covers the top area of the motherboard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disconnect the battery by slowly pulling the power belt (using a flat-head screwdriver or any sharp object).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the USB cable to Mi-Pad end (but not the PC end).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a short circuit between the two tiny pads inside the MicroSD card slot using a metal object or wire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the USB cable to the PC end.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If done properly, the PC will detect a &lt;em&gt;Nvidia Boot Recovery for Mobile&lt;/em&gt; USB device and then you can flash your stock ROM using Xiaomi’s flashing software, Mi Flash Tool, thus putting the life back into your tablet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Magic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most tricky and magical aspect of this whole process is the short-circuiting in step four. Firstly, it is not easily diagnosable. The Nvidia USB driver is in fact detected by the PC even if you don’t create the short-circuit (but the battery needs to be disconnected of course), but then it will disappear instantly and you won’t get the time to flash your stock ROM. For some unknown laws of electricity (or maybe the laws coded inside this Nvidia driver), the short-circuit may not work instantly the first time. You’ll create the short-circuit, connect to the USB port and hear the Windows beep sound for USB connection, but moments later you will hear another beep of disconnection. If that happens, you’ll have to disconnect the USB cable and repeat from step-4: Create the short-circuit again and reconnect to the USB port - I had to do this about 50 times before the connection was stable enough for me to flash the ROM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some forum posts advice you to plug in the power belt at exactly the same time as the USB connection is detected in the PC. However, I’ve found that its not true. Not once did I put the power belt back in the whole process until the ROM had been flashed completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Weapon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use any metallic object to create the short circuit, even a tiny wire could be used. The important thing is that those two minuscule pads inside the MicroSD slot are connected by a metal. Personally, I used this tiny pin that came with the booklet along with the Mi-Pad itself!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Short circuit on the two pads inside the MicroSD slot" class="size-large" src="/uploads/old/short.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All I did was place that pin inside the MicroSD slot, so it created a bridge on top of those two pads, and supported the pin using any available object (in this case a screwdriver).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll also need a 2.0mm screwdriver to open the back-panel above the motherboard. Please remember that opening those screws are going to void your warranty (which is going to happen in any case since you either tried to root or used the &lt;code class="highlighter-rouge"&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt; command to rewrite partitions in order to reach this stage!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On your Windows PC, you need the following installed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Latest version of Mi Flash Tool (Can be downloaded &lt;a href="http://xiaomitips.com/download/miui-rom-flashing-tool/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Latest version of Mi Phone Manager PC Suite for the Nvidia drivers (Can be downloaded &lt;a href="http://en.miui.com/thread-92720-1-1.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can download the whole bundled software from &lt;a href="https://androidmtk.com/download-xiaomi-mi-flash-tool"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that comes with Mi Flash Tool, NVidia Drivers and ADB Drivers too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll also need to download the latest MIUI stock ROM for Mi-Pad from &lt;a href="http://en.miui.com/download-229.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and extract somewhere on your PC to flash it later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your short-circuit works and the connection stays stable, waste no more time. Just fire up the Mi Flash tool and select the path to the ROM image you just extracted and click the flash button. Once the flash is successful, assemble back your Mi-Pad and on pressing the power button, you should see this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="MI-Pad Recovered" src="/uploads/old/MIUI.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep a cool mind and do it, it can be done! If you can’t do it, try and find a mobile repair shop nearby or catch a tech enthusiast in your circle who can do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://xiaomi.eu/community/threads/mipad-is-dead-brick.25162/page-3#post-228543"&gt;Post by original Russian Hacker (BogNik) who did it first&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://xiaomitips.com/download/miui-rom-flashing-tool/"&gt;Latest Mi Flash Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.miui.com/thread-92720-1-1.html"&gt;Latest Mi Phone Manager PC Suite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://androidmtk.com/download-xiaomi-mi-flash-tool"&gt;Latest Bundled Software - Flash Tool with Nvidia and ADB Drivers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.miui.com/download-229.html"&gt;Latest MIUI stock ROM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Android"></category><category term="Hardware"></category><category term="Xiaomi"></category><category term="How To"></category></entry><entry><title>7 Reasons I would prefer an Android Phone over WP8</title><link href="/blog/2014/12/7-reasons-i-would-prefer-an-android-phone-over-wp8.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-19T09:42:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-12-19T09:42:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-12-19:/blog/2014/12/7-reasons-i-would-prefer-an-android-phone-over-wp8.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My existing phone is a &lt;em&gt;Karbonn A30&lt;/em&gt; running &lt;em&gt;Android ICS&lt;/em&gt; and my next phone is going to be an Android phone too. Both as a &lt;strong&gt;user&lt;/strong&gt; and as a &lt;strong&gt;developer&lt;/strong&gt;, I've come upon the realization that Android provides a much better user experience and overall satisfaction in mobile computing.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/old/Android_WP8_Feature_compare.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Android-WP8 Feature comparison" src="/uploads/old/Android_WP8_Feature_compare.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My existing phone is a &lt;em&gt;Karbonn A30&lt;/em&gt; running &lt;em&gt;Android ICS&lt;/em&gt; and my next phone is going to be an Android phone too. Both as a &lt;strong&gt;user&lt;/strong&gt; and as a &lt;strong&gt;developer&lt;/strong&gt;, I've come upon the realization that Android provides a much better user experience and overall satisfaction in mobile computing.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/old/Android_WP8_Feature_compare.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Android-WP8 Feature comparison" src="/uploads/old/Android_WP8_Feature_compare.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had briefly considered using Windows Phone once, but I've discarded that idea after giving it a trial run. Here are the 7 reasons why I would only go for a phone running the Android Operating system and not WP8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More features:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This is one of the primary reasons a user buys any product, let alone a cell-phone. Android clearly wins in this department as it provides more features (out-of-the-box) compared to WP8. Just open the android settings menu and compare it to the feature-deprived WP8 settings screen to prove this to yourself. WP settings doesn't even allow you to perform basic things like:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up a custom mp3 ringtone (You need a PC with Zune software running for that.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up bluetooth options (No advanced options like bluetooth tethering )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brightness settings are only low, medium and high (whereas Android provides a slider to set a custom percentage).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No built-in file manager (At least the lumia 520 I tested did not)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not enough power stats (Android shows a complete run-down of what apps ate how much battery life, WP doesn't even show the exact percent of battery remaining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More options for tethering:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; One of the major reasons that I use my phone is to tether my phone's internet, so as to use it on my laptop. Android provides me three options to do this: Wifi tethering (aka Access point), Bluetooth tethering, USB tethering. WP8 only provides Wifi sharing and that too is not quite customizable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More free apps:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The Google play store is full of professional apps (many of them free, too). For instance, ES3 is a file-manager, archiver, FTP-manager and backup-manager combined. This app is not freely available on WP8 and I doubt the paid version would be having the features comparable to android version. Other examples are Terminal-IDE  (A fully-fledged IDE) and QPython (A fully-fledged programming environment!) that are both freely available on Android.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Opensource technologies:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Android stack completely rests on Open source technologies. The Linux kernel, Apache Harmony and Dalvik VM are all Opensource components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Supported by Google:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Another reason to go with Android is that it is actively developed and supported by Google Inc, a company whose interests directly harmonize with that of the end-users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;More options for the Developer:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Even as a developer, you will have a much better time developing an Android app than a WP8 app. First of all, the development tools (EclipseADT and Android SDK) are pretty well-documented on &lt;a href="http://developer.android.com"&gt;Android Developer site&lt;/a&gt;. Secondly, these are opensource tools that run on all platforms including Linux and OSX. On the other hand, developing a WP8 app requires Windows 8 64 bit version and nothing else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;No vendor lock-in:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; As a corollary to point 4, there is no vendor lock-in when you go for Android. Because the source code of android OS is freely available from the &lt;a href="http://source.android.com"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt;, you can customize it if you need to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content></entry></feed>