<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Prahlad Yeri's Blog - Blogging</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/feeds/blogging.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://prahladyeri.github.io/</id><updated>2022-02-11T10:00:00+05:30</updated><subtitle>Educate and solve problems is my mantra. I'm skilled in web development and a quick learner, I also like blogging and contributing to open source.</subtitle><entry><title>Title case headlines are highly overrated</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2022/02/title-case-headlines-are-highly-overrated.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-02-11T10:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-02-11T10:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2022-02-11:/blog/2022/02/title-case-headlines-are-highly-overrated.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are various misconceptions in the blogging world surrounding title cases these days and there are many who advocate putting all your headlines in title case, some of them are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"It Looks Good"&lt;/strong&gt;: The most commonly thrown argument is that title cases are somehow aesthetically pleasing or they look good …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are various misconceptions in the blogging world surrounding title cases these days and there are many who advocate putting all your headlines in title case, some of them are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"It Looks Good"&lt;/strong&gt;: The most commonly thrown argument is that title cases are somehow aesthetically pleasing or they look good. However, the "looks good" factor is obviously subjective, some may like it and others may not. In my opinion, they seem to be more readable initially but after a while, they get irritating. What also needs to be said here is that the &lt;code&gt;h1&lt;/code&gt; tag does its job remarkably well, and the fonts and styling you use have a much greater impact here than whether you use a title case headline or not. For example, there are display classes in Bootstrap CSS framework (&lt;code&gt;d-1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;d-2&lt;/code&gt;, etc.) which make the letters even bolder and larger than normal &lt;code&gt;h1&lt;/code&gt; tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"Good for SEO"&lt;/strong&gt;: That they're good for SEO is yet another baseless argument. Google not only keeps its search algorithm well hidden but also changes it from time to time, there is no way for us to know whether or not they consider title case headlines for page ranking. However, if you perform a casual analysis of what kind of search results typically come up on the first page of your search results, you'll find a good mix of both title and sentence cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="desk" src="/uploads/code-coding-computer-data-574073.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important thing for readability is not a title case headline but maintaining consistency and that's much easier to do with the sentence or proper casing. Writing title case headlines is difficult because there are no universally accepted rules to determine which words to capitalize. It's generally accepted that nouns and adjectives must be capitalized but what about minor and commonly used terms like &lt;code&gt;the&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;of&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;to&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;like&lt;/code&gt;, etc.? Should we always capitalize some of them and if so, which ones? APA might differ from MLA style for some classes of words, your own grammar school might say something else! With sentence casing, there is always a natural consistency and less confusion because you just capitalize the first letter of the sentence and proper nouns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, some people want to push the narrative that title case headlines are somehow the norm or what the "experts" do but that's not true at all. The opinion is highly divided on this matter and this can be easily understood by performing a simple case study. The most professional and authoritative blogs who's works can be trusted are reputed news agencies or circulating magazines. You can perform this case study for any topic you want but since the Ukraine conflict is presently a hot topic, I did a simple Google search for "Ukraine news" and this is what I found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="title-case-headlines-are-overrated" src="/uploads/title-case-headlines-are-overrated.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only two news agencies (NDTV and News-18) have used title case, all the others including Hindustan Times, India Today, The Hindu, etc. have all used sentence casing. Needless to say, these are all highly reputed news agencies who's reportage people trust in both mainstream and social media. And as you can see, both title and sentence casing can be observed across the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, they follow this rule consistently too, most NDTV articles will have title case headlines and most India Today articles will follow sentence casing. With these examples, we can clearly see that there is no such norm that title casing should be followed at all times, and there is a good opinion divide between title and sentence casing. As I said earlier, personally I prefer sentence casing because not only do the headlines look better (at least to me!) but it's also very easy to define and less confusing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Writing"></category></entry><entry><title>How to organize your research for blog posts in 2022: A comprehensive guide</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2022/02/how-to-organize-your-research-for-blog-posts-in-2022-a-comprehensive-guide.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-02-07T10:10:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-02-07T10:10:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2022-02-07:/blog/2022/02/how-to-organize-your-research-for-blog-posts-in-2022-a-comprehensive-guide.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most challenging aspects of blogging is how to perform research and more importantly, organizing your research. As a technology blogger, I face this problem too, so some days ago, I did some research on... guess what? Yep, on how to organize research for writing articles or blog …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most challenging aspects of blogging is how to perform research and more importantly, organizing your research. As a technology blogger, I face this problem too, so some days ago, I did some research on... guess what? Yep, on how to organize research for writing articles or blog posts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="grocery cart" src="/uploads/grocery-cart-with-item-1005638.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A natural question that arises here is why should bloggers organize their research in the first place? There are many benefits to it, the most obvious is that because your writing reflects your thinking or thought process itself, getting into a regular habit of organizing your research work will then force your mind to organize your thought patterns too. This will, in the longer term, make you a better thinking and more intellectual person, and also help your creativity as your creative mind will now have a much larger and more organized arsenal of knowledge to come up with more ideas more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bad news, though, is that organizing research isn't an exact science, there is no one true way of doing it and every blogger evolves their own method over time. Having said that, as Katie Holmes &lt;a href="https://beryliveylibrary.wordpress.com/2018/02/13/organize-research/"&gt;describes in this article&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;"Librarians are known for a few things. Aside from loving cardigans and tea, we tend to be Amy Santiago levels of organized"&lt;/em&gt;. The article borrows some great ideas from librarians in this regard!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before straightaway diving into online research, let's determine what kind of research we are doing first. Have you already decided on the exact topic and/or headline of your next article and doing research just for gathering content? Or you don't yet know the topic and you're just doing some "general" research around a broader topic to then find out what exactly to blog about? The latter is called preliminary research and you should ideally do it prior to performing the actual "heavy" research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, preliminary research is something I happen to do almost always as that's how I come up with ideas for my next blog post. Accordingly, you may organize your note taking process. What I personally do is I've created two folders called "research" and "drafts" for the preliminary and  actual kinds of research respectively. Inside the research folder, I have various topical subfolders like tech, health, lifestyle, etc. in which I store notes in the form of plain text files. The drafts folder is for my actual writing projects, in this folder go one file for each article I'm in the process of writing and these are in markdown format. The end result may look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;├───drafts
│   │   how-to-get-near-perfect-shave-in-less-than-5-rupees.md
│   │   how-to-understand-determinism-with-flowchart-analogy.md
│   │   how-to-maximize-happiness-with-dmu-philosophy.md
│   │   why-we-should-support-community-distros-like-mint.md
│   │
│   └───fiction
│
└───research
    ├───finance
    │       nifty.yaml
    │
    ├───health
    │       yoga.yaml
    │
    ├───horticulture
    │       organic-fertilizers.yaml
    │
    ├───lifestyle
    │       frugal-living.yaml
    │       yoga.yaml
    │
    ├───tech
    │       github.yaml
    │       linux.yaml
    │       microsoft.yaml
    │
    └───writing
            organization.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The markdown files are initially filled with chunks and subheadings, all organized into a rough outline until I finally call the research done and then start organizing the actual content of the draft. This way, I gradually come up with an article's content bit by bit, as if picking up parts of a big jigsaw puzzle and joining them one by one. Trust me, doing all of this might sound very "boring" or monotonous initially but it'll be real fun once you start getting the hang of it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, you can also maintain something called &lt;em&gt;Concept Maps&lt;/em&gt; which Katie also describes in her article. It's a form of organizing your brainstorming process. You start with a topic say &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt;. Then you might link various areas of applications to it, say &lt;code&gt;web development&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;data analysis&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;machine learning&lt;/code&gt;, etc. Then you think of various frameworks and apps like &lt;code&gt;flask&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;django&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;mezzanine&lt;/code&gt;, etc. So, you can have something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Web Development
  ├───Flask
  ├───Django
  ├───Mezzanine
Machine Learning
  ├───NLTK  
  ├───TensorFlow
Data Analysis
  ├───Numpy
  ├───Pandas
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You don't need any specific app or software to maintain this, you can even maintain them in something called &lt;code&gt;yaml&lt;/code&gt; files (*.yaml). These are plain text files with support for hierarchical text storage and can work wonders for tasks like this if you have a good text editor such as Notepad++ or Visual Studio Code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the preliminary research text files, I create one for each major topic. For example, &lt;code&gt;github&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;microsoft&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;windows&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;linux&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;, etc. (under technology). In each file, I'll add a link or citation (for the source) and few bullet points for each below it (this is what Katie calls "cue cards" or "annotations"). For example, in case of &lt;code&gt;github&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;:
    + Microsoft acquires Github Inc.
    + Speculations arise as to future of &lt;span class="nb"&gt;source&lt;/span&gt; hosting facility.
    + Competitor Gitlab pushes on advertising.
    + Many developers thinking of migrating to Gitlab.

&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;: https://www.businessinsider.in/Microsoft-has-been-talking-about-buying-GitHub-a-startup-at-the-center-of-the-software-world-last-valued-at-2-billion/articleshow/64420905.cms
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A simple organizational trick I follow here is that I append the bullet points in my own words with a plus sign (+) whereas a dash or minus sign indicates that the quote is lifted from the article as it is. So, "Microsoft acquires Github Inc." above is my own note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizing information collected from various sources in this manner forces you to think like a journalist and believe me, you'll come up with much more creative, original and refreshing content as a blogger, once you start practicing this strategy! It's not necessary that you put just bullet points, you can have direct quotes in quotation marks, brief annotations or notes in your own language, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing is to write down ideas as they come to you. Say you're reading this above source (the Business Insider article) and one blog post idea suddenly strikes you: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2018/06/microsofts-github-acquisition-an-unbiased-perspective.html"&gt;Microsoft's Github Acquisition - A Perspective
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Then stop reading it and create a new markdown file for this article in the drafts folder, and start writing down things as they come to your mind. Ideally, you'll also have the &lt;code&gt;github&lt;/code&gt; file in the research folder open in a separate tab of your text editor to borrow sources and bullet points from there as and when needed. This is the most &lt;em&gt;organic&lt;/em&gt; way of coming up with articles and you can never go wrong with this method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, the idea for the github article may arise sometime later. For example, after you have had a good night sleep and wake up with a fresh mind next day. But since you already have everything organized in your computer now, it'll be much easier to just open up your preliminary research folder and skim through your notes and thus equipping yourself with a much better chance of coming up with a good quality article. If you hadn't organized this, you'd have to go through your browser's history, bookmarks, etc., and do a tremendous amount of head-scratching just to recall what good points you had read yesterday!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, it'll also help you to read about the three types of sources as described in &lt;a href="https://habitsofatravellingarchaeologist.com/tips-for-organizing-sources-for-research-papers/"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; by Smiti Nathan of the &lt;em&gt;Habits of a Travelling Archeologist&lt;/em&gt; blog. As bloggers, we mostly base our research on tertiary sources (like online news blogs, articles, Wikipedia, etc.) but it's also important to be aware of primary and secondary sources in your field too if you want to establish some reputation as expert in your subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article also describes various ways of finding sources like getting to know your nearby librarians, &lt;a href="https://scholar.google.com/"&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt;, locating literature reviews, checking out &lt;a href="https://www.academia.edu/"&gt;Academia&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/"&gt;ResearchGate&lt;/a&gt;, engaging with live sources (experts in various fields), etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More inspiration for organizing writing content can be found in Mike Hanski's article titled &lt;a href="https://inspirationfeed.com/5-writing-tips-how-to-organize-your-research/"&gt;5 Writing Tips: How to Organize your Research&lt;/a&gt;. Hanski starts by describing the importance of quality research which is highly lacking in today's blogosphere and then proceeds to give some important tips like Record Everything, Always Be Ready for Genius to Strike, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I feel that organizing research isn't easy or straightforward, but if you're motivated enough and prepared to dedicate it some time, you can do it successfully and evolve your own organization process over time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Keyword Research"></category><category term="SEO"></category><category term="Research"></category></entry><entry><title>Dealing with writer's block: The ultimate checklist</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2022/01/dealing-with-writers-block-the-ultimate-checklist.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-24T10:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-01-24T10:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2022-01-24:/blog/2022/01/dealing-with-writers-block-the-ultimate-checklist.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Writer's Block is something that even the best among us struggle with occasionally and there is no easy answer to it. I've been following techniques such as the &lt;a href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2022/01/how-to-generate-a-never-ending-supply-of-blog-posts.html"&gt;10 content-types method&lt;/a&gt; to brainstorm and come up with ideas but all such techniques have a limit, eventually the block finds some …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Writer's Block is something that even the best among us struggle with occasionally and there is no easy answer to it. I've been following techniques such as the &lt;a href="https://prahladyeri.com/blog/2022/01/how-to-generate-a-never-ending-supply-of-blog-posts.html"&gt;10 content-types method&lt;/a&gt; to brainstorm and come up with ideas but all such techniques have a limit, eventually the block finds some way or the other to creep in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="laptop coffee" src="/uploads/laptop-coffee-mobile.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no easy answer to the problem of Writer's Block because it's almost a "Wholesome Evil"! It's not an easy thing to diagnose because there could be several reasons causing it. You could be stuck at home during a lockdown and having missed the familiar places you often keep visiting, your mind may not be giving you it's usual supplies of ideas? Maybe you are suffering from depression which is acting as a blocker that keeps ideas from sprouting up without you knowing? The possibilities are almost infinite, Writer's Block almost feels like a mystery because the subconscious mind is a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps that's why when I posted this question in front of all writers in the "Creative Writing" Facebook group, &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/wherecreativitylives/posts/10158713599531104/"&gt;the answers I received&lt;/a&gt; were as diverse and unique. In this post, I'm attempting to create a checklist of such reasons, so if you happen to be a writer who is currently suffering from a block, it may help you to go through each one and then who knows, you might stumble across a few that will give you the Eureka moment and diagnose the cause of your block in an instant!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Procrastination&lt;/strong&gt;. I think procrastination is easily one of the commonest reasons for a block in most people. In fact, most writers themselves admit it as this is the top voted answer! However, what causes procrastination can also be an unsolvable mystery sometimes as it could be happening due to some other unknown reason (such as a need for perfection or even depression).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of creative ideas&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the second voted answer and also very common among writers. This problem may not be easy to solve as you may have to study and do some reading of your subject matter in order to come up with more ideas (at least in case of non-fiction writing). In case of fiction writing, it's not so straightforward. But again, visiting new places, meeting new people, and even doing something differently from your daily schedule that breaks the monotony can often trigger distant memories which might act as a catalyst for generating new ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imposter syndrome&lt;/strong&gt;. This third voted reason is also quite common today, especially in young engineers. The need for perfection becomes so urgent and chronic sometimes that your very belief system takes a hit, you fail to even acknowledge the possibility that you can produce great works of writing. And on those rare occasions when you do write something good, this sly and cunning mental force succeeds in convincing you that it wasn't really &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; who did that! That's what Imposter syndrome really is. &lt;em&gt;"You are just being an &lt;/em&gt;imposter&lt;em&gt; after all, how can you accomplish such a great thing"&lt;/em&gt;, is what your mind says. Very often, this is the real reason behind what appears to be procrastination and we don't know that consciously. As one comment rightly says, &lt;em&gt;"Writers need to give themselves permission to suck"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Need for Perfection&lt;/strong&gt;. This very much relates to and is sometimes linked to imposter syndrome. But regardless, the need for perfection often prevents any creative endeavor from progressing, it's not just about writing. Almost every IT Project has a project manager sitting on top of a programmer, do you know why? Coding is a creative endeavor and left on their own, programmers have the tendency to keep on churning builds after builds of an app just to "perfect" some features! But the manager has to worry about deadlines too, so they keep nudging the programmer every now and then to just get it done soon! In case of a writing project (where we are the manager ourselves!), we must keep reminding ourselves that it's better to have a slightly less than perfect plot or scene and move on than keep "perfecting" a particular plot or scene until all Eternity!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Busy schedule&lt;/strong&gt;. Though it's less common, writers often miss this unknowingly. Have you considered the possibility that the reason you're unable to write is that you're not dedicating enough time to the writing process itself? While writing can often times be a creative and liberating process, it isn't always easy. Depending on the kind of writing you're doing, you may have to spend lots of time on research, character building, plotting, outlining, etc. And to be honest, once you actually start doing it, the nitty gritty of it may well turn out to be more mundane and monotonous than creative. Is it the case that the very dread of it is causing you to not allocate enough time for writing in the first place? Ask yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distractions&lt;/strong&gt;. Based on a good number of comments, this seems to be a cause too. Many writers are unable to focus or pay attention to their writing due to mundane distractions like loud noises of TV or music systems, road traffic, loud speakers, etc. And while a lot of these can be fixed to a certain extent like using ear-plugs, going on a retreat or cafe to write, etc., the real solution is to &lt;em&gt;change ourselves and increase tolerance&lt;/em&gt;. Intolerance towards external noises is a relatively new phenomenon largely induced by modern technology which is designed to encourage a lifestyle of &lt;em&gt;constant divided attention&lt;/em&gt; (through notification sounds, multiple app windows and workspaces, etc). A regular practice of mindfulness meditation is, in fact, a great way to counter this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depression or ADHD&lt;/strong&gt;. One of the most downplayed reasons of writer's block is depression. Depression is a far more common malady in society than most people seem to think it is. Fear of writing (or achieving success through writing) is also a manifestation of depression. It's a taboo in the society (at least in India) to even acknowledge that one has depression, it's perceived to be some kind of weakness in humans instead of just another problem to be solved. This, in turn, causes people to consciously keep suppressing its existence in the mind. Many a times, you may not even know that your depression could be preventing you from writing unless you actually sit and ponder about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of Confidence&lt;/strong&gt;. This generally relates to either &lt;em&gt;Depression&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Imposter syndrome&lt;/em&gt; described above. If you're not feeling confident enough to write, it's generally because of these two reasons, go ponder about it and think what you can do about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ditz Factor/Cluttered Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;. This reason stated in the comments section sort of opened my eyes! The dictionary meaning of "ditz" is &lt;em&gt;A flighty and disorganized person&lt;/em&gt;. And indeed, like in any other endeavor, planning and organization should be a prerequisite before you start writing, perhaps even more so in this case as there could be so many impediments to writing in the first place (as this list suggests!). Maybe stop all your activities and just think for a while about what you want to write, then organize by outlining or making bullet points or doing some brainstorming? There are modern tools available for this today such as &lt;a href="https://trends.google.com/trends/explore"&gt;Google Trends&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://answerthepublic.com/"&gt;Answer The Public&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://ads.google.com/aw/keywordplanner/"&gt;Google Keyword Planner Tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Need to think "outside the box"&lt;/strong&gt;. Out of box thinking is a major component of creativity, that's how you manage to stand away from the crowd and bring new ideas to the table. But what will cause you to think more out of the box, or what is preventing you from doing so is not a very easy question to answer. One thing you may want to do is keep going through this checklist again and again until you find it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of Passion&lt;/strong&gt;. Have you considered the possibility that you're writing about the wrong subject? Writing flows naturally when you're interested in a topic, that's when it's easy to focus there. Mind you, passion can also be "generated" or "feigned" initially until it comes naturally with the "zone factor". But if you're writing about a topic for a very long time and still facing a block, then it's time you ponder on this point. Are you even passionate about what you're writing? If not, maybe try writing about something else for a change? Even writing about general non-fiction things (such as this blog post) can help you a lot until you find your exact passion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of Enthusiasm/Energy&lt;/strong&gt;. Sometimes, you're passionate about a subject and you want to write passionately but you don't find the energy or enthusiasm to sit on the desk for a few hours and actually do it. Ask yourself what's causing this to you. If it's a question of loss of focus or fickle mindedness, you can try focus meditation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of Discipline&lt;/strong&gt;. The creative people of present age seem to have a general distaste for the concept of discipline! But we are not talking about authoritarian regimes here, &lt;em&gt;self discipline&lt;/em&gt; is a structure or format of rules you subject &lt;em&gt;yourself&lt;/em&gt; to and it might actually be a good thing. Discipline will help you in those darkest of hours when you're engrossed in the nitty gritty of research/outlining/plotting, when writing has suddenly turned from creative to mundane and you feel like just stopping it. At this point, it's a good question to ask yourself - Is lack of discipline causing your writer's block?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creative Exhaustion&lt;/strong&gt;. This is very much a thing, isn't it? There is only so much you can come up with on a given topic in a given span of time. And this applies to both fiction and non-fiction. Are you trying to churn out too much writing than you can handle? If so, maybe take a break and come back. It's also not necessary that you should write about only one topic. You can write both fiction and non-fiction, you can even write journals or blog posts, you can even write self-notes or poetry for a while until you get back to your primary domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Failure to Walk&lt;/strong&gt;. Seems like a very silly reason but still included for the sake of completion. But then again, you can also apply the trial-error method to writing process and if all else fails, why not just go out and take a walk? Maybe it'll actually work out for you!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"Other Mysterious Force"&lt;/strong&gt;. If you sincerely tried out or at least pondered all the above points and still suffering from a block, then it'll be due to some other "mysterious" reason but rest assured that it'll still just be mysterious, not supernatural! In this case, you can use the "trial-error" approach, see what works best for you and what doesn't. In general, going through your daily schedule and making adjustments to it usually helps. The primary agenda should be about allocating more time for writing and also more reading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Writing"></category></entry><entry><title>How to generate a never ending supply of blog posts</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2022/01/how-to-generate-a-never-ending-supply-of-blog-posts.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-15T10:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-01-15T10:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2022-01-15:/blog/2022/01/how-to-generate-a-never-ending-supply-of-blog-posts.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you're suffering from writer's block or don't know what to write about or how to research content for your next blog post, this guide will help you. There are just about 10 basic content-types or patterns around which weblog articles are written these days, and by creatively combining them …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you're suffering from writer's block or don't know what to write about or how to research content for your next blog post, this guide will help you. There are just about 10 basic content-types or patterns around which weblog articles are written these days, and by creatively combining them with your subject matter expertise or your knowledge of hobbies, crafts or something else, you can potentially end up with a never ending or infinite supply of blog posts throughout the year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#contentTypes"&gt;The 10 basic content-types.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#interestsAndHobbies"&gt;Your Interests, Hobbies and Subject Matter Expertise.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#combOneAndTwo"&gt;Combine the 1 and 2!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#staticAndDynamicPostIdeas"&gt;Static and Dynamic Post Ideas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this sounds very simple to you, that's because it really is. Writing isn't a rocket science, all you need is a little organization and you need to keep some time aside for it, and you need to keep practicing it until you gain perfection like any other art. Once you start getting into the "zone", writing will feel as natural to you as photosynthesis!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="laptop coffee" src="/uploads/laptop-coffee-mobile.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;!--img alt="python code" src="/uploads/laptop-coffee-mobile.jpeg" class="right-aligned" --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='contentTypes'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The 10 content-types&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listicle:&lt;/strong&gt; A List formatted article or listicle is one of the most commonly found these days. The ones titled like "40+ Ways of Doing Something" fall in this category. These articles are relatively easy to write because you're typically only playing the role of "information organizer" here. It's totally fine if you describe each item in the list only briefly and provide links to other resources like Wikipedia, etc. where subject matter experts deal with that item in much depth or detail. Checklists and Cheat-Sheets are also types of a Listicle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How-To Guides:&lt;/strong&gt; A How-To guide (such as this one!) is also very common because these are quite informational and Googlers are always hunting for these! Blogging is still a relatively new and inexact science in the digital world, even the best SEO and Internet Marketing companies are always struggling for eyeballs by constantly improving content quality, gathering street cred on social media, creating backlinks, etc. While these techniques seem to work to a limited extent, it's not an exact science and there is no guaranteeing that a given blog post is going to bring eyeballs for lifetime once written (despite all the SEO/SEM tactics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gone past are those days when people actually used to read the "user manuals" that came with their products, these days most of them simply Google that information and typically land up on a "How-To" article that describes that product. And it could well be yours if you've dealt with the subject thoroughly and it happens to be an in-demand topic or niche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infographics:&lt;/strong&gt; Infographics is the modern way of enhancing the content quality and improving the information value of an article. If you're creative with graphics software like Inkscape or Gimp, you can design infographics which is nothing but a summary of what you want to say in picture format with words creatively sprinkled here and there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparison - X vs Y:&lt;/strong&gt; Comparisons are also as commonly looked up by Googlers as How-To Guides! I myself remember the countless times I've run searches like "PHP vs Python", "Wordpress vs Drupal", "Django vs Flask", "WinForms vs WPF", "MySQL vs PGSQL", etc. You may be a programmer but the informational article you're writing doesn't necessarily have to be about programming. You may well decide to write a technical article pertaining to your subject matter too. But you may as well compare just anything you may come across or want to compare, even &lt;em&gt;Apples vs Oranges&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Democrats vs Republicans&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate Review:&lt;/strong&gt; Review posts are also highly sought for these days for almost same reason as Comparison posts. Was a new product or service recently launched in your area of expertise? Or even a drastically changed new version of an existing product or software? If yes, write a post about it and it'll be in high demand because a new product typically arrives with lots of bugs, issues, doubts, new ways of doing existing things, etc. and users are always looking for a helping hand there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ultimate Guide:&lt;/strong&gt; Ultimate guides are detailed write of a particular idea or process which people often find difficult or confusing because there is never one straightforward or easy way of doing things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case Study:&lt;/strong&gt; These are the ones titled, &lt;em&gt;XYZ Program: How to make 15K or More Each Month&lt;/em&gt;, or similar. It could be a Udemy course or an IT project or even an infrastructure project implemented somewhere or anything else of interest. People are always looking for case studies in order to study them and learn from them. Agile and Software Engineering is another area where constant improvement is needed, relatively new field, inexact science and all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Story:&lt;/strong&gt; Most personal stories these days feature along the lines of &lt;em&gt;How I moved from 1K to 10K in 18 Months&lt;/em&gt; but they don't necessarily have to be. Making money online is just  one of the hot topics out there and frankly, it's highly over-saturated! In fact, you'll have a far better chance of ranking and getting page-views in that little niche or expertise area you might be having than here. A story could be about anything, it could be about the struggles of your life in childhood, school and college days, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Informational Story (Industry News, World Events):&lt;/strong&gt; The blogger can occasionally wear the journalist's shoes too by writing informational posts! Industry news relating your subject matter is something you're most naturally equipped to write a lot about, but it doesn't necessarily have to be. You can write an informational post about just any and every topic on earth from politics to weather. The dinner table conversations going on in your home (mostly about politics!) are an ideal thing you can convert into an informational article and publish on your blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='interestsAndHobbies'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Your Interests, Hobbies and Subject Matter Expertise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These can be almost anything but generally fall in the following broad categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology:&lt;/strong&gt; Whether you're a programmer, tester, QA/QC analyst or designer, you'll definitely have lot's of things to write and share about your field and even workplace, a weblog is an ideal platform to do this. It doesn't even have to be about IT, you could even be an Auto Engineer or Aeronotics Engineer or someone else. Each person has a unique story to tell and so do you, and the Internet is always all ears for that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finance:&lt;/strong&gt; If you work in the finance industry as an accountant or book-keeper or even a clerk, you'll still have a lot to share about the changing dynamics in your field, the computerization and use of open source software, changing policies of the government and due to effects of COVID, etc. Personal finance, and tips on saving money are also great topics to write on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Politics:&lt;/strong&gt; Politics is almost like the bread and butter of netizens who read blogs, there are no other kind of articles that go viral in such a short time as those relating to politics! If you have a flair for writing creative and interesting matter on this topic, you're definitely going to have a field day here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food:&lt;/strong&gt; There are millions of food blogs out there already and yet, some new content turns up every single day! Some new delicious recipe or a variant of existing recipe or something different you tried out today? You can also blog a lot about topics relating to cuisine like health effects of various spices and vegetables, veganism and vegetarianism, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="combOneAndTwo"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Combine the 1 and 2!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the real magic happens when you apply the basic content types to your knowledge or what you already happen to know! For example, do you shop a lot? You can then write a comparison post on say, &lt;em&gt;Walmart vs Tesco&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Big Bazaar vs Reliance Mart&lt;/em&gt;! If you're a Python engineer, &lt;em&gt;Flask vs Django&lt;/em&gt; is the ideal post in that case. And how about &lt;em&gt;Veganism vs Vegetarianism&lt;/em&gt;! The possibilities of doing this are almost infinite!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="staticAndDynamicPostIdeas"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Static and Dynamic Post Ideas.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above process of creatively combining your knowledge with basic content types will give you what is called &lt;em&gt;static posts&lt;/em&gt;. They're called as such because the content is mostly static in nature (though their relevance will progressively get lower with time), and hence such posts can be planned in advance and organized using what is popularly called &lt;em&gt;blogging calendar&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, because of how the Internet works, you're only allowed to share a couple of posts each day on social media platforms at most, so you must plan your content accordingly. Writer's muse typically doesn't work evenly, they come and go in leaps and bounds. But you can't afford to don't interact at all for a week and then dump all articles at once on Twitter, that will most likely flag you as a spammer! What bloggers typically do is they write their drafts in advance (leaps and bounds creativity!) and then schedule to publish them evenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from these static posts which you can plan in advance, you can also write a &lt;em&gt;dynamic post&lt;/em&gt; which can be written and published any time. Some big event took place in your field all of a sudden, yesterday? You'll have a lot to say about that topic, so you can come up with a new post and publish it immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your content strategy should involve publishing a mix of both static and dynamic posts frequently. Having only dynamic posts won't give you much content at all because there will be only so much happening in your given field every day. On the other hand, having static posts only will make your blogging process feel more monotonous and less creative. So, having a mix of both is a good ideal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="SEO"></category></entry><entry><title>How to set your blogspot blog for twitter card validation</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2021/01/how-to-set-your-blogspot-blog-for-twitter-card-validation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-18T09:55:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-01-18T09:55:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2021-01-18:/blog/2021/01/how-to-set-your-blogspot-blog-for-twitter-card-validation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the first things you want to do after publishing your blog is to share it with rest of the world and twitter is how most of you folks do it, right? But when you share your link in a tweet, you want it to expand into a proper …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the first things you want to do after publishing your blog is to share it with rest of the world and twitter is how most of you folks do it, right? But when you share your link in a tweet, you want it to expand into a proper card like this. But with Google's Blogspot blogs, it doesn't happen by default (at least as of today) even though it should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="twitter-card-blogger" src="/uploads/twitter-card-blogger.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what you must do in order for your blog's links to expand on twitter in the card format. Please note that if you change your theme later, you must redo this exercise each time as the new theme entirely rewrites the HTML template.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to Theme =&amp;gt; Customize =&amp;gt; Edit HTML and open the HTML editor window for the blog template.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press "Control+F" and search for this phrase:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;b:includable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;post&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;post&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search it multiple times to make sure. In some templates, there are more than one of these sections and in those cases, we are interested in the last one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just hit &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;enter&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to create some blank space just below this tag start line and enter the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Twitter Card Tags --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;@prahladyeri&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:site&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;@prahladyeri&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:creator&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;b:if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;cond&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;data:post.firstImageUrl&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;summary_large_image&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:card&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c"&gt;&amp;lt;!-- summary_large_image or any other your card types --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;expr:content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;data:post.firstImageUrl&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:image&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;b:elseif&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;cond&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;data:blog.postImageUrl&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;summary&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:card&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;expr:content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;data:blog.postImageUrl&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:image&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;b:elseif&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;cond&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;data:blog.postImageThumbnailUrl&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;summary&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:card&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;expr:content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;data:blog.postImageThumbnailUrl&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:image&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;b:else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;summary&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:card&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-vCbJYZxPF80/XErJHU_gi7I/AAAAAAAACGU/WGznlnB-K8AnpZunzlHYuaxg6c1TA5UfwCPcBGAYYCw/s320/pexels-photo-261577.jpeg&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;twitter:image&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;b:if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please remember to change the &lt;code&gt;twitter:site&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;twitter:creator&lt;/code&gt; and the last &lt;code&gt;twitter:image&lt;/code&gt; meta tags (which is for the default image in case none is found in your post) as per what suits you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you do this and save the template, visit the &lt;a href="https://cards-dev.twitter.com/validator"&gt;Twitter Card Validation Page&lt;/a&gt; to verify that your blog link expands into a proper card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, you are ready to publish your blogspot link through a tweet and share it with the rest of the world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Blogspot"></category></entry><entry><title>DIY Keyword research for small bloggers using absolutely free tools</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2020/12/diy-keyword-research-for-small-bloggers-using-absolutely-free-tools.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-06T11:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-06T11:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2020-12-06:/blog/2020/12/diy-keyword-research-for-small-bloggers-using-absolutely-free-tools.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are a plethora of keyword research tools available in the market such as &lt;a href="https://www.semrush.com/"&gt;SEMRush&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://ahrefs.com/dashboard"&gt;ahrefs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://kwfinder.com/"&gt;KWFinder&lt;/a&gt;, etc. and while a subscription to them makes sense if you are a small company or startup, it definitely doesn't for small bloggers who work with a limited budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="python code" src="/uploads/laptop-coffee-mobile.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even if you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are a plethora of keyword research tools available in the market such as &lt;a href="https://www.semrush.com/"&gt;SEMRush&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://ahrefs.com/dashboard"&gt;ahrefs&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://kwfinder.com/"&gt;KWFinder&lt;/a&gt;, etc. and while a subscription to them makes sense if you are a small company or startup, it definitely doesn't for small bloggers who work with a limited budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="python code" src="/uploads/laptop-coffee-mobile.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even if you have an absolutely zero budget, you can still perform decent keyword research and get the exact same results that these popular web services offer. However, you won't be served that information on a platter and you will have to work for it and setup your own workflow after sourcing inputs or raw material from various freely available tools. You must also know a little bit of scripting/programming and be prepared to write some scripts in a language like python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each blogger or researcher may have a different workflow with respect to keyword research, mine involves the following two tools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ads.google.com/aw/keywordplanner/"&gt;Google Keyword Planner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://answerthepublic.com/"&gt;AnswerThePublic.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both are excellent and robust freely available tools (though the latter gets you only a limited number of searches each day which is fine if you're a small blogger who posts only few times a week).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, writing any article involves the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determination of the topic and/or niche you want to publish about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research and gather information or sources about it (like books, wikipedia, online blogs, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actually write the article.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give it a decent or captivating headline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performing keyword research beforehand will help you with almost all these steps extensively. Firstly, it will help you determine which topic or niche you must blog about so that people actually find your content through search engines. In other words, you shouldn't end up writing an excellent piece about a topic which:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody is interested in (low search volume).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has so high competition that it's very difficult to rank on the first page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the two areas which you must actively avoid if you want to blog for visibility or getting web traffic. Of course, there are hobby bloggers who post just for the sake of fun or writing passion and that's fine too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming to the process of niche determination using keyword research, it involves two tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out which keywords related to our broader topic are currently in vogue or trending.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out which among those related keywords have a combination of good search volume and less ranking difficulty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Google Keyword Planner, both these tasks can be clubbed into one as it provides ways to both discover new keywords and getting search volume and forecasts for a given bunch of keywords (see below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Google Keyword Planner Tool" src="/uploads/google_keyword_planner_tool.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An alternative process of niche determination involves using ATP (answerthepublic.com) for the first task as it provides a richer set of related keywords which are questions or slightly longer phrases which have the potential for attracting long tail search volume. You then input these longer keywords provided by ATP to the second part of the Google Planner Tool ("Get search volume and forecasts"). But keep in mind that you can't just lift the keywords from ATP and enter them directly to Google Keyword Planner tool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is where scripting comes into picture. The CSV data exported by ATP has to be sanitized to the proper format (extra columns removed) so that it can be then entered to the Google Keyword Planner Tool. Scripting is also needed to store the output CSV from Google Planner to a proper database. Personally, I prefer &lt;code&gt;sqlite&lt;/code&gt; but &lt;code&gt;mysql&lt;/code&gt; is fine too. Google's output CSV has almost everything you need, almost everything which the other subscription based services provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Google Keyword Planner Results" src="/uploads/google_keyword_planner_results.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the only catch is that it's a DIY. You need to write your own program or script which imports this output to your database tables and stores data in the respective fields. "Avg. monthly searches" is quite apparent, you can use a long integer column called &lt;code&gt;searches&lt;/code&gt; to store this. "Competition" tells you qualitatively whether it's high/medium/low for that keyword, and "Competition (Index Value)" does the same quantitatively. It's an index value ranging from 0 to 100 and often referred to as KD (Keyword Difficulty) in the other popular tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've built your own workflow with automated scripts that involves importing and sanitizing data from ATP/Google, and storing it to a local database, you should be able to get what you want with a simple SQL query such as this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;select keyword from keywords where keyword like &amp;#39;%flask%&amp;#39; and searches &amp;gt;= 1000 and comp_idx &amp;lt; 30;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This will return all keywords in the &lt;code&gt;python flask&lt;/code&gt; niche which has a good search volume (1000 or above) and less difficulty to rank (competition index is less than 30). You can then proceed to use those keywords for writing your article which will now have a greater visibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A paid tool like SEMRush or ahrefs would have given you the exact same results as this SQL query but your solution is custom developed and more importantly, suited to your own work-flow. The only difference is that your database won't be having billions keywords at the start but it will grow organically and gradually as you keep writing articles and keep researching new content.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Keyword Research"></category><category term="SEO"></category></entry><entry><title>Is it good SEO or good content that drives traffic to your blog? - A causal analysis</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2020/08/is-it-good-seo-or-good-content-that-drives-traffic-to-your-blog-a-causal-analysis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-16T19:12:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-08-16T19:12:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2020-08-16:/blog/2020/08/is-it-good-seo-or-good-content-that-drives-traffic-to-your-blog-a-causal-analysis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to content publishing, there are basically two camps in the blogging world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "Content is King" camp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "SEO" camp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first camp insists that it's good content that entirely drives traffic to your blog or website. The second camp insists that it's good Search Engine Optimization …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to content publishing, there are basically two camps in the blogging world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "Content is King" camp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "SEO" camp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first camp insists that it's good content that entirely drives traffic to your blog or website. The second camp insists that it's good Search Engine Optimization (SEO) techniques like keyword research and relevant meta tags that does it by standing up to the search engine algorithms that determine the page ranking for each link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth (obviously) lies somewhere in the middle. There used to be a time in the 1990s (and probably early 2000s) when you could easily fool the Google search algorithm into making your page rank on top by merely spamming it with good keywords. But that started changing as the algorithms got smarter, today they are able to separate the wheat from the chaff. Today, they are able to tell the difference between good content and bad, or do they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, SEO should work only to the extent of supply/demand of relevant information. In other words, to the extent that people searching for online booking of flight tickets is greater than people searching for flight simulator games, the content related to former must rank above for most queries related to "flights" and thus they should bag a larger number of "hits" overall than the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But among all the "online flight booking" websites, how does the Google algorithm decide which ones to put on top and which ones at the bottom? How does it know that makemytrip.com and goibibo.com should rank higher than cleartrip.com and air.irctc.co.in for an Indian visitor? Or for that matter, how does it know that expedia.co.uk and skyscanner.net should be placed higher than momondo.co.uk or wegotravel.co.uk for a UK visitor?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this is where SEO and keyword research come into play which supposedly has some influence on that algorithm. SEO proponents like to think that their proposed measures (like filling the right meta tags, populating the page with right keywords, etc.) play a role in making makemytrip.com rank higher than cleartrip.com in Google searches. But can that really be true? Common sense suggests that search algorithms are a whole lot more complex beasts today than they once were and are influenced by just way too many things to create such a causal relationship:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Links (inbound and outbound)&lt;/strong&gt;. They play a large role in making the ranking decision. It could be the fact that makemytrip.com has a lot more links flowing in from highly reputable sites than air.irctc.co.in, so the algorithm is considering that in ranking. And of course, they should all be good (organic) links with no evidence of foul play! Now, trying to influence one's own site's ranking by throwing their links across various social media sites is an SEO technique called "link building" and is a slightly grey area. Do it too much and the search engines might ban your site or blog entirely in today's age. Done correctly, link building provides a good initial boost of popularity, it's a kind of marketing dude who goes across each home and tells good thinks about your product. But if the dude tries to be too intrusive or pushy, he might get blocked from the apartment. Thus, link building is more of a marketing trick than SEO technique in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keywords&lt;/strong&gt;. Well, they sometimes do work but I'd like to think of them as the effect of a well ranked page, not the cause. In retrospect, it explains how the page's content got ranked above its peers by the ranking algorithm but trying to replicate that strategy on another site by attempting to use more of those keywords may not always be successful. Trying to reduce textual content to mere keywords is like trying to reduce the human mind and emotions to mere neurons and synapses in the brain! They do play a huge role in the thinking process, but we humans are definitely more than our brain cells. That's the problem with many of today's so called "SEO Experts", they are pushing keyword research as some kind of a silver bullet to page ranking while ignoring everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content quality&lt;/strong&gt;. Ultimately, it's good content that every googler is really searching for! It's definitely not very easy to create good textual content and that's because writing is not an easy craft. It takes a lot of effort to come up with good content periodically and this difficulty is what has given rise to the whole SEO industry! It's my unpopular and controversial opinion that in an ideal world, SEO shouldn't be needed at all (except to the extent of finding out what kind of content people are searching for (demand), so that you may write content relevant to that (supply)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, trying to meet supply with demand is a common sense discipline, I wouldn't call it SEO at all! But you don't really need keyword research to tell you that do you? If you are an industry veteran who has some experience under your belt, don't you already know what is the trendiest subject in your industry? As a php programmer, for example, you must know that Laravel and Symfony are far more trendy these days than CodeIgniter or CakePHP. That doesn't mean that you shouldn't write articles on CodeIgniter, by all means you should if that's your area of expertise! But you must also be aware that those articles won't be catching as many eyeballs as the ones on Laravel or Symfony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same is the case in regard to Angular, React and Vue.js in the JavaScript world. You can probably rank much higher by writing on any of these frameworks instead of something like Backbone.js or Ember.js. All it takes is a little bit of reading and presence on social media to know that the former topics are in lot more demand than latter. Consequently, if you are a blogger who writes for adsense income or a freelance copywriter who sells content for a living, you'll know better to write more on the former topics than the latter. On the other hand, if you are a hobbyist blogger who writes for self-fulfillment and your interest in Backbone/Ember, you will write about the latter subjects even if they are less in demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate between the "Content is King" and "SEO" camps will probably continue for decades to come, but it all depends on who you are and what you hope to gain from SEO (or some of it's aspects called &lt;em&gt;content marketing&lt;/em&gt;). If you are a blogger or writer, my advice for you is to focus on mastering the art of churning great content frequently than trying to master the art of SEO.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="SEO"></category></entry><entry><title>Migrating Disqus comments into Wordpress</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2020/03/comments-migration-from-disqus-to-wordpress.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-11T13:25:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-03-11T13:25:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2020-03-11:/blog/2020/03/comments-migration-from-disqus-to-wordpress.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Further to my earlier blog post about &lt;a href="/blog/2017/09/demystifying-comments-migration-from-disqus-to-wordpress.html"&gt;How to Import Disqus comments into Wordpress&lt;/a&gt;, I've found that script solution to be a bit trickier for first time users who want to migrate disqus comments from their earlier blog to the new wordpress blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PHP Code" src="/uploads/code-php.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;disqus_parse.php&lt;/code&gt; is exactly the same …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Further to my earlier blog post about &lt;a href="/blog/2017/09/demystifying-comments-migration-from-disqus-to-wordpress.html"&gt;How to Import Disqus comments into Wordpress&lt;/a&gt;, I've found that script solution to be a bit trickier for first time users who want to migrate disqus comments from their earlier blog to the new wordpress blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PHP Code" src="/uploads/code-php.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;disqus_parse.php&lt;/code&gt; is exactly the same as it is because the parsing logic hasn't changed. However, a lot has changed in actual running of the console script (&lt;code&gt;console.php&lt;/code&gt;), so I've updated the same as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modified the URL check which ensures that disqus post's URL path is the same as Wordpress post's URL path. I've found that its much more effective to match only the "path" portions of the respective URLs instead of including the entire domain, so I used &lt;code&gt;parse_url&lt;/code&gt; PHP function accordingly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$cpath = parse_url($comment['url'], PHP_URL_PATH);
$tpath = parse_url($t_url, PHP_URL_PATH);
if ($cpath === $tpath) {
...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Added a &lt;code&gt;$sleep_interval&lt;/code&gt; parameter at the top of the script (default value is 2), this is needed sometimes because some Wordpress installations throw the error &lt;em&gt;"You are posting comments too quickly"&lt;/em&gt; when you try to append comments through a script. If this happens, you'll have to increase this parameter's value to 6 or sometimes 11 depending on the commenting user's status. If you want to avoid this check altogether and insert comments quickly, you can temporarily add the below line to the bottom of your &lt;code&gt;functions.php&lt;/code&gt; (but remember to revert back later once your comments are migrated!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;add_filter(&amp;#39;comment_flood_filter&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;__return_false&amp;#39;);
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;$post-&amp;gt;author-&amp;gt;name&lt;/code&gt; XML value may be in the array form sometimes, so I've added that check:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if (is_array($comment['name'])) {
    $comment_author = (string)$comment['name'][0];
}
else {
    $comment_author = (string)$comment['name'];
}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passed the &lt;code&gt;$avoid_die&lt;/code&gt; parameter as &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;a href="https://developer.wordpress.org/reference/functions/wp_new_comment/"&gt;wp_new_comment&lt;/a&gt; function as its more useful and practical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are the links to the latest scripts which you must run from inside a plugin directory such as &lt;code&gt;/wp-content/plugins/test/&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;console.php:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/prahladyeri/e22e4e232416ff841be670601b396c62"&gt;https://gist.github.com/prahladyeri/e22e4e232416ff841be670601b396c62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;disqus_parse.php:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/prahladyeri/d1e19d8a6d0c7ff23fe3e15f9050b6d3"&gt;https://gist.github.com/prahladyeri/d1e19d8a6d0c7ff23fe3e15f9050b6d3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Disqus"></category><category term="Wordpress"></category></entry><entry><title>How to import Disqus comments into Wordpress</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2017/09/demystifying-comments-migration-from-disqus-to-wordpress.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-07T02:01:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-09-07T02:01:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2017-09-07:/blog/2017/09/demystifying-comments-migration-from-disqus-to-wordpress.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;**Update**&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="/blog/2020/03/comments-migration-from-disqus-to-wordpress.html"&gt;Also check out this recent post which has further fixes and refactoring done to the console.php script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, I had switched from a self-hosted wordpress blog to a statically generated (Jekyll) blog hosted on Github Pages. For a commenting system, Disqus was quite an easy choice …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;**Update**&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="/blog/2020/03/comments-migration-from-disqus-to-wordpress.html"&gt;Also check out this recent post which has further fixes and refactoring done to the console.php script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, I had switched from a self-hosted wordpress blog to a statically generated (Jekyll) blog hosted on Github Pages. For a commenting system, Disqus was quite an easy choice at that time since it was zero hassle for us site owners, and Disqus did all the heavy lifting from filtering the comments to storing and displaying them.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/uploads/2017/09/pexels-photo-262508.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Blog" class="size-full wp-image-372" height="197" src="/uploads/2017/09/pexels-photo-262508.jpg" width="297"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as time went on, I started realizing that implementing a static blog was not quite the right thing. Firstly, there were &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disqus#Criticism_and_privacy_concerns"&gt;privacy issues&lt;/a&gt; around Disqus because of which many readers of my blog were discouraged from commenting. Secondly, the concept of a "static site" itself felt quite constraining to me as I couldn't implement things like contact form or a questionnaire to interact with my viewers. As a result, I decided to switch back to a plain old self-hosted wordpress blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, importing the posts was quite straightforward using the Jekyll generated RSS feed link that was pretty straightforward to use. In case you don't have it in your Jekyll blog, its very easy to write one using liquid template. Just create a file named &lt;strong&gt;rss.xml&lt;/strong&gt; in your root folder with below contents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version=&amp;quot;1.0&amp;quot; encoding=&amp;quot;UTF-8&amp;quot;?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;rss&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;version=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;2.0&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;xmlns:atom=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;channel&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;site.name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;xml_escape&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt; - Articles&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;description&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;site.description&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;%}{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;site.description&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;xml_escape&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}{%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;endif&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/description&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;link&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="cp"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;site.url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/link&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="cp"&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;post&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;site.posts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="cp"&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;unless&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;post.link&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;item&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;post.title&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;xml_escape&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;description&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;post.content&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;xml_escape&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/description&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;pubDate&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;post.date&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;%a, %d %b %Y %H:%M:%S %z&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/pubDate&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;link&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="cp"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;site.url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;post.url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/link&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;guid&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;isPermaLink=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;true&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;site.url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}{{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;post.url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/guid&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/item&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="cp"&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;endunless&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="cp"&gt;{%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;endfor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/channel&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/rss&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once you generate the blog, you can import all posts into your wordpress by referring to the &lt;strong&gt;/rss.xml&lt;/strong&gt; url on your existing Jekyll blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the bigger issue here was importing the Disqus comments, becuase while Disqus does allow you to &lt;a href="https://help.disqus.com/customer/portal/articles/472149-comments-export"&gt;export a dump of your site comments&lt;/a&gt;, their XML format is pretty weird and isn't the standard one used by wordpress and other blogging systems, as a result of which there aren't too many ready tools for importing comments from this format to any other system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I had to write my own Wordpress importer tool. Since I did not want to go through the hassle of learning to create an "admin plugin" with all the bells and whistles, I decided to write a simple PHP console script to import the XML as mentioned &lt;a href="https://wordpress.stackexchange.com/a/76466/52396"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All I needed were two scripts: A parser script to parse the XML output of Disqus comments dump, and secondly, a wordpress handler that loops through these comments and imports them one by one by matching the post's url attribute and running &lt;strong&gt;wp_new_comment()&lt;/strong&gt; to insert the comment (you can also use the older &lt;strong&gt;wp_insert_comment()&lt;/strong&gt;, but its not the recommended way according to the wordpress codex).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the source code for both these files. First one, &lt;strong&gt;console.php&lt;/strong&gt; is the wordpress handler that you need to run, passing the path of the Disqus comments dump file. And &lt;strong&gt;disqus_parse.php&lt;/strong&gt; is the parser which is called internally by console.php. You need to copy these two files anywhere inside your WP folder structure (I copied them to &lt;strong&gt;/wp-content/plugins/test/&lt;/strong&gt; folder), and run the console.php from the command line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;console.php:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/prahladyeri/e22e4e232416ff841be670601b396c62"&gt;https://gist.github.com/prahladyeri/e22e4e232416ff841be670601b396c62&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;disqus_parse.php&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/prahladyeri/d1e19d8a6d0c7ff23fe3e15f9050b6d3"&gt;https://gist.github.com/prahladyeri/d1e19d8a6d0c7ff23fe3e15f9050b6d3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, just keep one thing in mind before running the console.php. Your wordpress system might throw an exception in case it detects too many comments being inserted in a loop. To suppress that exception, you need to add the following line of code to the end of your theme's &lt;strong&gt;functions.php&lt;/strong&gt; to disable the comment flood filter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;add_filter(&amp;#39;comment_flood_filter&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;__return_false&amp;#39;);
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, remember to comment that line once you are done importing the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Disqus"></category><category term="Wordpress"></category></entry><entry><title>How to know whether my blog post will attract traffic or not</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2015/06/how-to-know-whether-my-blog-post-will-attract-traffic-or-not.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-10T18:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-06-10T18:30:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2015-06-10:/blog/2015/06/how-to-know-whether-my-blog-post-will-attract-traffic-or-not.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the evergreen topics for discussions in the blogging world is SEO, and especially the various ways of attracting bless of the all-pervading search engines to one’s own site or blog. There are various ways to approach this problem, some of the popular ones are:&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using meta tags …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the evergreen topics for discussions in the blogging world is SEO, and especially the various ways of attracting bless of the all-pervading search engines to one’s own site or blog. There are various ways to approach this problem, some of the popular ones are:&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using meta tags like &lt;code&gt;keyword&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;description&lt;/code&gt; to attract the search engines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performing keyword research (using Google Adword tool or similar).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting Link juice through social media marketing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiring SEO experts or web designers to get some arcane suggestions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But lost in these technical fads, people are forgetting one basic foundation upon which the internet is built: &lt;code&gt;CONTENT IS KING&lt;/code&gt;. Yes, the sad truth is that Google (or Yahoo/Bing for that matter) cannot be fooled by any of these tools in the &lt;code&gt;long term&lt;/code&gt;. Doing some social media marketing on Facebook might place your article on #1 position for a short period of time, but sooner or later, Google will figure out whether your content is actually worth it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do you write good content, and also ensure that it has some uniqueness that the million other sites on the internet don’t already have? Well, I can’t help you with the first question. Since &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; know what your area of expertise is, only you can come up with a good topic and subject-matter for your blog or site. For instance, Web Development is my area of expertise, and I came up with this particular topic you are reading right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I can certainly help you with the second question! Doing some research on this matter and performing a topic-wise traffic analysis of my own blog, has proven to me this one thing: &lt;code&gt;CONTENT IS KING&lt;/code&gt;. So, my method of figuring out whether your article/post will rock or not, is based upon this simple canon. Once you decide the topic and subject-matter of your next blog post, do this simple reality check before you even bother drafting it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost every Googler is looking for a specific solution for a problem or issue, be it shopping for a product, knowing a url address or researching something. So, your next post or article should solve that problem in order to pass the &lt;code&gt;CONTENT&lt;/code&gt; test. To get a quick idea of the competition, perform a Google search from the point of view of your potential Googler! A glance at the results will instantly tell you whether this problem is already solved, and by how many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, before publishing this article, I did this simple Google search:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;How to know whether my blog post will attract traffic or not
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And this is what I got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="How to know whether my blog post will attract traffic or not" src="/uploads/old/how-to-know-whether-blog-topic-gets-traffic.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All those are top ranking sites and deserve to be on page one (no offence meant to them). However, for someone specifically looking for a solution to this question (agreed, however small that set of users be), none of them have an immediate answer that could be surmised by the search result summary. Whilst they are all making clear points about &lt;code&gt;WAYS&lt;/code&gt; to increase search engine traffic, none of them talks about knowing, in priory, whether a given method will work or not. So, at least for this particular query (maybe used by about 1% of all bloggers), my blog post deserves to be amongst those page one results - and sure it will, because it has the only one thing that matters for Google - &lt;code&gt;CONTENT&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Blogging"></category><category term="Wordpress"></category><category term="How To"></category></entry></feed>