<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Prahlad Yeri's Blog - Technology</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/feeds/technology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://prahladyeri.github.io/</id><updated>2020-12-14T21:00:00+05:30</updated><subtitle>Educate and solve problems is my mantra. I'm skilled in web development and a quick learner, I also like blogging and contributing to open source.</subtitle><entry><title>Let's do more email</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2020/12/lets-do-more-email.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-14T21:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-14T21:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2020-12-14:/blog/2020/12/lets-do-more-email.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The privacy advocates have been quite vocally and vehemently discouraging the use of email since almost a decade now but contrary to popular opinion, I strongly believe that despite being old, Email is a wonderful technology and mode of communication with several benefits, and it can optionally be made fully …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The privacy advocates have been quite vocally and vehemently discouraging the use of email since almost a decade now but contrary to popular opinion, I strongly believe that despite being old, Email is a wonderful technology and mode of communication with several benefits, and it can optionally be made fully secure using plugins like Enigmail if desired by the correspondents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="envelope" src="/uploads/mesh.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are some reasons to keep using email as a mode of communication even in 2020 and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The old charm of "letter writing".&lt;/strong&gt; When did you last saw someone post a letter in an inland or envelope in the old fashioned way? Believe it or not but the good old "letter writing" has become an almost extinct skill these days. Email is the last remaining vestige of actual written communication which happens in a non-instantaneous way and records are preserved in an open format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No other alternatives.&lt;/strong&gt; A whole bunch of so called "IMs" or instant messaging apps have emerged over the years including Skype, WhatsApp, Telegram, Discord, etc. but none of them can replace the good old email. It's the only communication mode where the sender can respond with sizable content after taking a pause and undergoing a thought process instead of quickly "IMing" a few words through a mobile app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Based on open standards, isn't controlled by FANG or other big tech company.&lt;/strong&gt; Email is an open standard based on well established protocols like IMAP/SMTP/POP3/etc. It's the only communication mode which doesn't require a company like Google or Facebook to cooperate, consequently it isn't controlled by any one corporation and is thus a truly open technology owned by all of humanity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retention of records makes people more responsible in their tone and language.&lt;/strong&gt; Unlike "disappearing WhatsApp messages", emails can be archived and preserved for decades or even centuries with the technology we have. There is this recent modernist fetish for privacy which advises you against email only because comms can be preserved to be viewed later. But my argument is that if the communication is open to scrutiny, people will be more conscious of their tone and language. With "disappearing WhatsApp messages", people will be more inclined to use abusive language in their comms considering how difficult it is to gather them as evidence compared to email messages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can be made secure using tools like VPN and extensions like Enigmail.&lt;/strong&gt; It's a common misconception that Email communication is inherently insecure. Just as you can use SSL/TLS to make HTTP more secure, you can use plugins like Enigmail to digitally sign and even encrypt outgoing emails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you still refuse to use emails even after going through this thought process, it only means that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Either you have vested interests in FANG or other IM companies which thrive on standards not being open. OR&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have fallen for the propaganda spread by lobbyists belonging to the former category.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Internet"></category><category term="Email"></category></entry><entry><title>The gimp, the git and the sacred rules that govern offensive behavior</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2019/07/the-gimp-the-git-and-the-sacred-rules-that-govern-offensive-behavior.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-06T10:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-07-06T10:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2019-07-06:/blog/2019/07/the-gimp-the-git-and-the-sacred-rules-that-govern-offensive-behavior.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I was reading &lt;a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp/issues/3617"&gt;this heated debate&lt;/a&gt; on the GIMP issue tracker which was also perhaps the most discussed topic of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offensive behavior is a very serious and delicate topic, and needs to be handled with care. More importantly, rules should be codified which can objectively determine whether …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I was reading &lt;a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gimp/issues/3617"&gt;this heated debate&lt;/a&gt; on the GIMP issue tracker which was also perhaps the most discussed topic of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offensive behavior is a very serious and delicate topic, and needs to be handled with care. More importantly, rules should be codified which can objectively determine whether or not a term/sentence is offensive because anything left in the undecided grey area becomes a breeding ground for turf wars and hurt emotions like it happened yesterday!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rules are nothing but a listing of what is (and isn't) acceptable in a given domain based on a pre-defined logic. They don't necessarily have to be entirely objective or pre-determined too, sometimes their result might depend on context and sometimes they may also be subjective bringing in the bias of their creator. Considering the progress in neuro-linguistic programming, that day isn't far when an AI might decide on these rules automatically for us. Hence, its important to debate and settle matters on this topic now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the popularity of these codified rules, they may gain wide acceptability in the society at large but that doesn't mean they are perfect as they always keep evolving with time. In the ancient days, they were called "Hammurabi's code", then they started calling it "ten commandments" in the middle ages and these days, they are popularly known as CoC (Code of Conduct). But the thing that's common in them is rules governing human behavior which as I said are constantly evolving and sometimes subjective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That doesn't mean that there isn't an objective side to them though. The first thing we must do is determine what those objective words are which universally offends everyone (or at least most humans) without any question and in a deterministic way. If an AI were to decide on this, this is exactly how it will proceed. Let's call this the objective black list (OBL) or something, this list might include words like "ni**er", "sl**", "id**t", "wh**e", etc. There is no doubt that utterance of such words will mentally hurt most dudes or dudettes of the English speaking world. Except under certain contexts like meta discussions about curbing online offensive behavior and linguistic study, these words can be auto-blocked on most internet forums and I don't think many people will have any problem with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on the other hand, what about subjectively offensive words like gimp and git, how should we treat them? I'm calling them subjective because only a small subset of people find it offensive (like some  people on that linked post), not everyone. Personally, I didn't even knew that gimp actually means something else other than a linux paint application until I checked the merriam webster dictionary yesterday!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not a linguistic expert but from what I've learned from that discussion and &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/linux/comments/c9gvgf/consider_renaming_gimp_to_a_less_offensive_name/"&gt;this reddit post about the same topic&lt;/a&gt; is that the other meaning of gimp (a limp or crippled person) is only used by a small subset of British/European English speakers. Most American or Asian English speakers may not even be aware of this second meaning and gimp only means a linux app for them. So the question of taking offense never arises in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, it comes down to "individual vs collective liberties". The name change of a popular open source project like gimp isn't a trivial effort. You not only have to change the name in the build process (compile commands, make &amp;amp; config files, translation files, etc.), but all the various distros like ubuntu, debian, fedora, suse, etc. have to change it in their repositories too. Is it justifiable that such a large expense of time and efforts be incurred to keep a very small subset of individuals happy who happen to subjectively take offense in that project's name?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And besides, if we allow this to happen, where does the train stop? Speaking of translations, why should only the English speaking public have the luxury of taking offenses! gimp is translated into several other languages, why not the French, Spanish, Russian, Arabic and Hindi speaking public have a say in it too? I'm sure there is plenty of offense resembling substance to be found among all those linux packages if you consider all these languages!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you stick to English, what about other linux programs like git and fsck as the former is actually an offensive word whereas the latter resembles it to some extent (just as the GIMP acronym does)? I learned the meaning of git a very long time ago (perhaps in one of Harry Potter books), whereas GIMP was only an acronym for me until yesterday. And the first time I came across the version control system, I was mildly annoyed that what kind of a person would name a program as "git". But even then, I never found that word to be offensive or troubling at all. As time went on and I started using git and github for almost every project, I forgot that other meaning of git and only recall it when I come across it these days (like today!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But me, I'm a programmer and I can understand how a non-tech dude would feel about it. Especially if you are a Brit, I'm sure you'll take offense if anyone casually calls you a "git" in a conversation, irrespective of whether you are a programmer or not. But will you actually take offense at that word and take your fight to the git forums and ask them to rename that project? Is all that effort worth spending on a name change? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;if the whole world starts taking offense on some words used in technical contexts, can you even imagine how many hours of coding, testing, documentation, builds and project maintenance will be wasted on name change alone?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="Internet"></category></entry><entry><title>Growing intolerance and lack of compassion towards new developers on StackOverflow</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2019/05/growing-intolerance-and-lack-of-compassion-towards-new-developers-on-stackoverflow.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-16T19:59:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-16T19:59:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2019-05-16:/blog/2019/05/growing-intolerance-and-lack-of-compassion-towards-new-developers-on-stackoverflow.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;StackOverflow is the digital equivalent of the Holy See or the Holy Mecca when it comes to programming. It is that place where developers go visit when they don't have answers to their coding problems in a hope that the Gods of StackOverflow will help them solve it.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But lately …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;StackOverflow is the digital equivalent of the Holy See or the Holy Mecca when it comes to programming. It is that place where developers go visit when they don't have answers to their coding problems in a hope that the Gods of StackOverflow will help them solve it.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But lately, the Gods of StackOverflow seem to be exhibiting a lot of intolerance and impatience towards those who are still learning the craft of programming and new to it. There seems to be a growing belief or consensus that unless you already have a certain level of expertise, you don't belong here in our chamber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the example of this dude today who had &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/q/56167254/849365"&gt;a very simple question about jinja2 templates&lt;/a&gt;, a topic related to flask, a python web framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A question about jinja2, abruptly closed as a duplicate" class="wp-image-1132 size-large" height="458" src="/uploads/2019/05/so_closed_incorrectly-1024x458.png" width="1024"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A question about jinja2 abruptly closed as a duplicate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was about to answer this question when it was abruptly closed for being a duplicate. The person who closed this didn't even consider that a beginner coder (considering the reputation score) may not even know what the capabilities of jinja2 were. How the heck was s/he supposed to know that the answer to this question was to be found outside the context of jinja2? Everyone on this planet isn't a born expert in web development. The coder expected a solution in the context of jinja2 templates itself and the right way would have been to guide him/her and explain that this isn't possible through jinja2 but front-end scripting is required here. Then the answering post could proceed to provide a few helpful example links from StackOverflow or someplace else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to ask those intolerant ones: consider that you yourself could have needed this hand-holding and guidance when you were beginning to code some years earlier? Just because coding has become so easy and second nature to you now, it doesn't give you any right to behave with arrogance. Knowledge needs to be used with grace and caution, with power comes the responsibility of using that power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of behavior is quite common from what I've been reading lately on social media too and my observation today just confirms it. I hope that more and more senior developers develop compassion towards others and treat this site as the temple of knowledge which it really is, not an egotistical chamber to shut down other programmers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Social Networking"></category></entry><entry><title>A dark day for consumer rights - Right to repair bill killed in Canada thanks to corporate lobbying</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2019/05/a-dark-day-for-consumer-rights-right-to-repair-bill-killed-in-canada-thanks-to-corporate-lobbying.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-03T14:23:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-05-03T14:23:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2019-05-03:/blog/2019/05/a-dark-day-for-consumer-rights-right-to-repair-bill-killed-in-canada-thanks-to-corporate-lobbying.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When Linus Torvalds wrote the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux"&gt;Linux Kernel&lt;/a&gt; in 1991 or Ian Murdock first released the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debian"&gt;Debian OS&lt;/a&gt; in 1993, talking about the "openness" of a PC or the "right to repair it" would have been a laughable affair! 8086 was an open standard then (just as standards should be) and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When Linus Torvalds wrote the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux"&gt;Linux Kernel&lt;/a&gt; in 1991 or Ian Murdock first released the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debian"&gt;Debian OS&lt;/a&gt; in 1993, talking about the "openness" of a PC or the "right to repair it" would have been a laughable affair! 8086 was an open standard then (just as standards should be) and anybody was free to write an operating system for it (such as Linux), or user land utilities (such as GNU) or even define a desktop standard (such as Xorg).&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="random image" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-904" height="225" src="/uploads/2018/07/pexels-photo-261577-300x225.jpeg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in 2019, that's no longer the case with standards. Looks like humanity is going backward in terms of progress as standards are becoming more and more closed and proprietary instead of becoming open and transparent. Companies like Apple are successful in not only creating entire dependencies of such closed standards but are fighting tooth and nail so that their closed standards get a stamp from the legislature too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law makers of Ontario, Canada succumbed to this massive corporate lobbying today and &lt;a href="https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/9kxayy/right-to-repair-bill-killed-after-big-tech-lobbying-in-ontario"&gt;killed the "right to repair" bill before it could even see the lights of the day&lt;/a&gt;. This bill was asking for a very basic thing - the right to open your own device (which you've already paid for) and fix it for any problems. In order to empower a user to do this, the bill called for forcing tech companies like Apple to provide the following at a fair price:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repair Manual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Official Parts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diagnostic Tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something very basic, something the Stallmans and Torvalds of the world have already been doing since 90s. Canada sent a very wrong signal to the tech world today, this would have been the first such pro-consumer law in the world, if passed. &lt;a href="https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/evex8z/right-to-repair-advocates-are-hosting-youtube-town-halls-to-show-you-how-to-get-involved-in-the-movement"&gt;About 20 American states are also considering a similar right to repair bill&lt;/a&gt; and this sets a very wrong precedent to those decision makers. Both USA and Canada are highly developed countries and the whole world looks up to them for framing their own tech laws, so this is a very bad thing that happened today. I hope the American states will act sanely and pass this bill otherwise any hope left for open standards and protocols for the future generations will be lost. Since innovation blossoms in openness and gets stifled in closed environments, this will sound a death knell to innovation too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is now left to organizations like &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/"&gt;EFF&lt;/a&gt; and internet freedom activists like &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/"&gt;Richard Stallman&lt;/a&gt; to protest this decision and ensure some sanity in the tech world which is getting increasingly crony capitalistic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Internet"></category><category term="Open Source"></category></entry><entry><title>Foxy firefighters and the clash between individual and collective liberalism</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2019/02/foxy-firefighters-and-the-clash-between-individual-and-collective-liberalism.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-02T10:51:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-02-02T10:51:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2019-02-02:/blog/2019/02/foxy-firefighters-and-the-clash-between-individual-and-collective-liberalism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The biggest speculation in the tech industry these days concern net neutrality and the last week was no different. Whilst I'm happy that TRAI is clear on upholding the net neutrality in my own country, India, the clouds of doom could be clearly seen in USA as the FCC is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The biggest speculation in the tech industry these days concern net neutrality and the last week was no different. Whilst I'm happy that TRAI is clear on upholding the net neutrality in my own country, India, the clouds of doom could be clearly seen in USA as the FCC is trying hard to banish net neutrality and bring control of the Internet in the hands of a few large companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is quite worrying for Internet in general because the world looks up to the United States for laws governing the digital space, not India. What's hilarious is that the FCC is resorting to unbelievable arguments like &lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2019/02/throttling-of-firefighters-hurts-fcc-case-as-it-defends-net-neutrality-repeal/"&gt;broadband isn't a telecommunication service&lt;/a&gt; in their desperate attempt to repeal net neutrality. I hope the US legal system is smart enough to discard such illogical arguments and the light of justice prevails in the country where Internet was first invented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="random laptop image" class="size-medium wp-image-1087 aligncenter" height="200" src="/uploads/2019/02/laptop-1478822_1920-300x200.jpg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The positive thing though is that those fighting on the side of net neutrality are also strong in numbers and include &lt;a href="https://9to5mac.com/2019/02/01/save-net-neutrality/"&gt;companies like Reddit, Mozilla, Vimeo, etc. along with 22 state attorneys&lt;/a&gt;. Also, unbelievably, in the middle of this protest against repeal of net neutrality are a &lt;a href="https://abcnews.go.com/beta-story-container/Business/firefighters-join-mozilla-net-neutrality-fight-citing-public/story?id=60750432"&gt;bunch of fire fighters&lt;/a&gt; who also want net neutrality to prevail! Fire fighters of California are citing public safety as a reason to uphold net neutrality and logically so. According to the linked ABC news report, California witnessed the largest fire in its entire history and the firefighters encountered an unexpected danger - they couldn't communicate with their team members as Verizon was deliberately throttling and slowing down Internet speed on their phones. This is just a small sample of what could happen across the world if net neutrality was repealed for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2019/1/29/18202880/facebook-research-enterprise-root-certificate-onavo-techcrunch"&gt;Facebook seems to be offering teenagers 20/month in exchange for their phone activity data&lt;/a&gt;. While privacy advocates are all pitchforks on this happening and calling for Facebook to be made liable, this has a very large implication on the ever ongoing debate on &lt;strong&gt;"Individual Liberty vs Collective Liberty"&lt;/strong&gt;. For me, personally, it makes sense that digital privacy is a very important thing and online companies shouldn't be encouraged by allowing to run schemes like these when studies have shown that they already collect a whole lot of user data by default (location tracking, analytics, diagnostic data, etc.). Any other ration dude who has some knowledge of Information Technology will also think similarly, I suppose. However, if I try to advocate this knowledge to others and call for laws preventing such individual sale of private data, we are venturing into the area of collective liberalism, and here comes the danger of a clash happening between collective and individual liberalism. The thing is that those teenagers (however misguided they are), have full liberty to trade their private data with facebook or whatever social media company they want, and preventing them from doing that might be against the ethics of individual liberalism, that's just my few cents. In all probability, this debate could continue for years to come and so will the privacy debate, hopefully a solution will be found which is favorable and acceptable to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not the least, there are &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/feb/01/facebook-mental-health-study-happiness-delete-account"&gt;many studies like&lt;/a&gt; these sprouting up these days claiming that deleting Facebook or Twitter accounts bring happiness in people's lives. However, I want someone to perform another study into the mystery of why do so many people decidedly stay unhappy by constantly plugging into the social media sites!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Internet"></category><category term="News"></category></entry><entry><title>Docker trick: Running containers efficiently using a bash script</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2018/09/docker-trick-running-containers-efficiently-using-a-bash-script.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-14T10:59:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-09-14T10:59:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2018-09-14:/blog/2018/09/docker-trick-running-containers-efficiently-using-a-bash-script.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the basic problems with running a docker image is that its too easy to spew up multiple instances or containers of the same image. Consider running the following container for instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker run -it -e AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID=&amp;quot;test&amp;quot; -e AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY=&amp;quot;test&amp;quot; \
--net=host &amp;quot;prahladyeri/testimage:latest&amp;quot; /bin/bash
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the basic problems with running a docker image is that its too easy to spew up multiple instances or containers of the same image. Consider running the following container for instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker run -it -e AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID=&amp;quot;test&amp;quot; -e AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY=&amp;quot;test&amp;quot; \
--net=host &amp;quot;prahladyeri/testimage:latest&amp;quot; /bin/bash
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This will start a fresh container instance from image &lt;strong&gt;prahladyeri/testimage:latest&lt;/strong&gt; and you may optionally pass environment variables (using -e switch), and the /bin/bash argument to manually trigger a command inside the container instead of running the default one. However, once you exit the container, you don't have any control over that container &lt;em&gt;instance&lt;/em&gt;. Running the same "docker run" command as above is just going to spew another container instance for the same image, while the old one still stays in memory. Repeating this process multiple times is a wastage of invaluable memory and cores which isn't the goal of using docker at all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="docker-logo" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-1073" height="232" src="/uploads/2018/09/docker-logo-300x232.png" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more efficient way of handling things is to check the existence of a container instance already running for the image, and restart that one if required:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker ps -a -f &amp;quot;ancestor=prahladyeri/testimage:latest&amp;quot; -q -l
f7261ea890ce
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The above command returns the id of an already running container (if any), so using that you can just restart that same container without passing all the parameters again as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;docker start -i f7261ea890ce
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can automate this whole process by writing a single bash script called &lt;em&gt;start_container:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ch"&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;prahladyeri/testimage:latest&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;imgid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;docker ps -a -f &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;ancestor=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; -q -l&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; -z &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;creating new instance for &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  docker run -it -e &lt;span class="nv"&gt;AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;test&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; -e &lt;span class="nv"&gt;AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;test&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; --net&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;host &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; /bin/bash
&lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;instance found&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  docker start -i &lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;docker ps -a -f &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;ancestor=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$imgname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; -q -l&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Just replace the \$&lt;em&gt;imgname&lt;/em&gt; variable with that of your own image name, and pass any arguments you want (for example, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;-e AWS_KEY_ID&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;) to the container on line 7. This script will start a new container only if none are found already, otherwise, it will just restart an existing one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope you find this useful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Docker"></category><category term="Linux"></category></entry><entry><title>Beware of Uber's vomit fraud when booking a cab next time</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2018/07/beware-of-ubers-vomit-fraud-when-booking-a-cab-next-time.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-24T10:51:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-07-24T10:51:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2018-07-24:/blog/2018/07/beware-of-ubers-vomit-fraud-when-booking-a-cab-next-time.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;According to some recent reports by top technology blogs, Uber drivers have been reportedly engaging in an activity called "vomit fraud". Basically, Uber (and many other cab services too) allow their drivers to collect a fine of up to \$150 if their customer creates a mess in the cab (such …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;According to some recent reports by top technology blogs, Uber drivers have been reportedly engaging in an activity called "vomit fraud". Basically, Uber (and many other cab services too) allow their drivers to collect a fine of up to \$150 if their customer creates a mess in the cab (such as puking).&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we aren't talking about the occasional real puke or vomit here, drivers are reportedly exploiting this feature to fraudulently claim a "cleaning fee" even when no such thing was done by a customer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bmw-car-driving" class="alignnone wp-image-994 size-medium" height="200" src="/uploads/2018/07/bmw-car-driving-13781-300x200.jpg" width="300"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, according to &lt;a href="https://gizmodo.com/ubers-vomit-fraud-sounds-worse-than-surge-pricing-1827797566"&gt;this Gizmodo report&lt;/a&gt; a Miami resident was recently fined twice fraudulently for this. And whilst you might recover this fine by engaging with their customer care and maybe exchanging several emails with them, the process is almost infinitely tedious and there isn't a guarantee that you may get your money back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make things worse, as per this &lt;a href="https://mashable.com/2018/07/23/uber-vomit-fraud"&gt;Mashable report&lt;/a&gt;, a tech savvy driver may also photoshop a fake picture of a puke and provide it as evidence thus making your chances of recovering the fine almost zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice has become so rampant that the drivers are openly admitting doing this on social media platforms and treating it casually. From the linked Mashable report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&gt;&gt; &lt;em&gt;"lol vomit fraud is the oldest trick in my book," one Redditor — with &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/lyftdrivers/comments/8cdg8k/lyft_pickup_changed_rerouting/"&gt;a history&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/uberdrivers/comments/8b9olz/just_announced_rate_increases_for_drivers/"&gt;ride-hail related&lt;/a&gt; posts — &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/uberdrivers/comments/910kt8/its_called_vomit_fraud_and_it_could_make_your/e2v96m7/"&gt;wrote in r/uberdrivers&lt;/a&gt;. "I’ve successfully done it many times when [passengers] are rude, slam my doors, or make me wait too long. Makes them learn the hard way."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know what could be the solution to this other than some basic "street-smartness" by customers and maybe the built-in review system. If drivers who indulge in such fraudulent behavior are reported frequently and called upon by customers in their reviews, that should ideally purge the system of bad drivers in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Uber"></category></entry><entry><title>Alternative "Reddit like" social networking sites for the minimalists</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2018/07/alternative-reddit-like-social-networking-sites-for-the-minimalists.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-10T15:01:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-07-10T15:01:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2018-07-10:/blog/2018/07/alternative-reddit-like-social-networking-sites-for-the-minimalists.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Minimalists are those netizens who prefer websites that mostly contain rich and relevant textual content (with maybe bits of images sprinkled here and here), but certainly not auto-playing videos, flashy animations, animated gifs and motion ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making an excruciatingly heavy and painful website by combining all these things not only …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Minimalists are those netizens who prefer websites that mostly contain rich and relevant textual content (with maybe bits of images sprinkled here and here), but certainly not auto-playing videos, flashy animations, animated gifs and motion ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making an excruciatingly heavy and painful website by combining all these things not only take a toll on the server's back end resources, but is also a step back in the advancement of the Internet, not forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its quite evident now that we are in the tiny minority because all popularity metrics point towards non-minimalist social sites like Facebook, Twitter, Google Plus, etc. And to add to that agony, &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com"&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; has also decided to follow along the path of those other sites as we are being shunned to the &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com"&gt;old Reddit&lt;/a&gt;. Old Reddit is not just being shunned as legacy, but also in the process of being dismantled. That's because any new visitor who visits a subreddit will always be shown the new interface by default (even if the subreddit owners/mods happened to have created it on old Reddit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides, the user is also being gently prodded on to embrace the new version by various measures. For example, the default profile page of the user is the new profile page (even when visiting old.reddit.com, yeah!) and the only way to switch back to the older version is a small hidden switch in the preferences section that you wouldn't know exists unless you go there and scroll to the absolute bottom of the page!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Reddit Hidden Legacy Switch" class="size-full wp-image-892" height="463" src="/uploads/2018/07/reddit_hidden_legacy_switch.png" width="1051"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reddit Hidden Legacy Switch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a similar tone, when you logout from Reddit in order to log back in (using a different alt which is quite common on Reddit), you'll suddenly find that you are back in the new version and the header link and everything else points to the www.reddit.com, and not old.reddit.com! You'll be surprised to find that even if you switched your profile back to the legacy mode, other Redditors who visit your profile will still see the new version there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, Reddit is trying to send us a clear message: Fall in line with our new system or just get lost. And get lost we will, but the question is where? Certainly not Facebook, Twitter or Google Plus because that's not what a minimalist will want to use, even though they may have an account on one of these other sites just for being compatible with their non-minimalist friends, relatives, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I'm going to describe a few such social networking sites which are relatively minimalist, though all of them may not have the same charm as the good old Reddit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, lots of minimalist sites are either getting closed or turning into micro-niches that nobody except a certain section want to use. For instance, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newsvine"&gt;News Vine&lt;/a&gt; shut down recently, it was a collaborative journalistic platform where users contributed all kinds of stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also used to like &lt;a href="https://voat.co/"&gt;Voat&lt;/a&gt; very much, but recently there have been &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/SubredditDrama/comments/3gerlv/is_voat_becoming_reddit_for_racists_or_is_that/"&gt;reports that Voat is turning into a meeting place for right wing supremacists and those who like to troll online users based on their caste/ehtnicity.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/StumbleUpon"&gt;StumbleUpon&lt;/a&gt; was also recently shut down and transformed into something called Mix, I don't quite like the looks of the new design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there still seems to be some hope left as some minimalist sites do exist to fill this void:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;i) &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hacker News" src="/uploads/Y-Combinator1.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hacker News&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though Hacker News is a niche site for the technology niche, it sill tops my list because it is almost as minimal as you could get. Its a purely textual content site with neither images nor CSS transitions and perhaps that's how most of the technologists like it. The content quality on this site is also highly vetted and top notch, and definitely better than many popular subreddits where politics comes into the mix every now and then as the mods try to sneak in their own propagandas in the subreddit content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ii) &lt;a href="https://slashdot.org/"&gt;Slashdot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Slashdot" src="/uploads/Slashdot.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slashdot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two reasons to include &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slashdot"&gt;Slashdot&lt;/a&gt;in the list. Firstly, its a minimalist site, and secondly, it is owned by BizX LLC, the same company who acquired SourceForge after the huge fiasco in Jan, 2016. If most media reports are to be believed, the new owners are doing a great job of rebuilding SourceForge from its old tarnished image. The site design is also much better than the heavy ones like Google Plus, Facebook and Quora, Slashdot is also very light on loading server resources (HTML/CSS/JS) which I like a lot. Sites like Slashdot who strive to improve the user experience and UI efficiency like this deserve all the users in the world, yet its a funny world where these other heavy sites get all the attention! So, whom I should blame if not the users who visits these sites?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;iii) &lt;a href="https://hubski.com/"&gt;Hubski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hubski" src="/uploads/hubski.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hubski&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hubski was something that was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubski"&gt;designed from the ground up to be a reddit alternative&lt;/a&gt;, so it shouldn't disappoint you if you are looking for a reddit replacement. Hubski was started by Mark Katakowski as a clone of Hacker News, and the code is still in a Lisp dialect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;iv) &lt;a href="https://boards.4chan.org"&gt;4chan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="4chan" src="/uploads/4chan.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4chan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4chan is also a minimalist site like Reddit, but geared more towards Internet activism groups like Anonymous. A redditor should feel comfortable with their discussion thread UI which reminds you a bit of the old PHP bulletin boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;v) &lt;a href="https://snapzu.com"&gt;Snapzu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snapzu" class="wp-image-909 size-large" height="276" src="/uploads/2018/07/snapzu.com_-1024x484.png" width="584"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snapzu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snapzu is just like Reddit, only it has a more polished interface and they call their category pages "tribes" instead of subreddits, for instance &lt;a href="https://snapzu.com/t/technology"&gt;/t/technology&lt;/a&gt; is the technology tribe. However, you need to request an invite before joining, but apparently they dish them out pretty quickly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;vi) &lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastodon is yet another great site, not as minimal as reddit or slashdot, but much better than facebook and twitter. And the best thing is that its federated, so mastodon.social isn't the only instance, there are a &lt;a href="https://joinmastodon.org/"&gt;bunch of others&lt;/a&gt; too and they are all synced and federated in real time, whatever instance you be on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;vii) &lt;a href="https://www.quora.com"&gt;Quora&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Quora" class="size-full" height="289" src="/uploads/Quora.jpg" width="343"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quora&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quora isn't exactly minimal and I wasn't even going to include it in this list, but since we have so few (working) options left, Quora needs a place here at least temporarily. At least, its way too minimal than the likes of Facebook and Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;viii) &lt;a href="https://medium.com"&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Medium" class="size-full" height="329" src="/uploads/Medium_screenshot.png" width="302"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I included Quora, I thought why not Medium. To be honest, sites like Quora and Medium fall in the far end of minimalist sites and we are stuck with them only because of lack of options. Nevertheless, the content quality on Medium is quite good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ix) Update on 16th July, 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I came across one more strong contestant in the race for reddit alternatives called &lt;a href="https://raddle.me/"&gt;Raddle.me&lt;/a&gt;. It was built during September last year by some &lt;a href="https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/zm3wbj/radical-leftists-built-their-own-reddit-after-it-banned-them"&gt;"radical leftists" who felt that Reddit had wrongly banned them&lt;/a&gt;. Raddle.me does have a leftist bias, just as Voat has a rightist bias, but the interface and looks are pretty much what a minimalist Redditor will appreciate. Also, the site is built using PHP (Symfony and Doctrine), unlike Reddit which is built using Python (Pylons framework).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Raddle.me" class="size-full wp-image-948" height="641" src="/uploads/2018/07/raddleme.png" width="1366"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raddle.me&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;x) Update on 21st July, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two new addendums to this list are &lt;a href="https://saidit.net/"&gt;saidit.net&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://dev.lemmy.ml/"&gt;dev.lemmy.ml&lt;/a&gt;, and both are fascinating and remarkable projects in quest of a reddit replacement. The former is especially interesting because its based on the old classic/minimalist reddit source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="saidit.net" src="/uploads/saidit.net.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;saidit.net&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="dev.lemmy.ml" src="/uploads/dev.lemmy.ml.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dev.lemmy.ml&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reddit"></category><category term="Social Networking"></category></entry><entry><title>Why GPL isn't working - the Freedom vs Convenience Debate</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2018/06/why-gpl-isnt-working-the-freedom-vs-convenience-debate.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-29T15:02:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-06-29T15:02:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2018-06-29:/blog/2018/06/why-gpl-isnt-working-the-freedom-vs-convenience-debate.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What distinguishes &lt;strong&gt;GPL&lt;/strong&gt; from other freedom licenses is their &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_General_Public_License"&gt;premise&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GNU General Public License (GNU GPL or GPL) is a widely used &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_software_license" title="Free software license"&gt;free software license&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;strong&gt;guarantees&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End_user" title="End user"&gt;end users&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;strong&gt;freedom to run, study, share and modify the software&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPL or &lt;em&gt;copyleft&lt;/em&gt; strives for the freedom of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What distinguishes &lt;strong&gt;GPL&lt;/strong&gt; from other freedom licenses is their &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_General_Public_License"&gt;premise&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GNU General Public License (GNU GPL or GPL) is a widely used &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_software_license" title="Free software license"&gt;free software license&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;strong&gt;guarantees&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End_user" title="End user"&gt;end users&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;strong&gt;freedom to run, study, share and modify the software&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPL or &lt;em&gt;copyleft&lt;/em&gt; strives for the freedom of the plebians of the community, and guarantees them absolute freedom on the source code of a software to not just view it, but also run and modify it, and most importantly, to share it with whoever they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the real world, the plebians don't want freedom, they want functionality and convenience. If a closed-source solution gives them the convenience to do a task with least efforts, they are happily going to embrace that solution despite knowing that both their privacy and freedom is at stake by using that solution. The proof of this fact is usage and popularity metrics of many such apps. For example, almost everyone knows about the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook%E2%80%93Cambridge_Analytica_data_scandal"&gt;Facebook-Cambridge Analytica privacy scandal&lt;/a&gt; that happened recently, and yet how many people switched to open and freedom respecting platforms like &lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/s/social/"&gt;GNU/Social&lt;/a&gt; after that? Ask your friends about them and there is a good chance that 9 out of 10 would not have even heard about platforms like Mastodon and GNU/Social.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its the same situation with messengers too. For instance, &lt;a href="https://jitsi.org/"&gt;Jitsi&lt;/a&gt; is a freedom respecting messenger software and yet people use only &lt;strong&gt;Skype&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;WhatsApp&lt;/strong&gt; for messaging. Not only are Skype and WhatsApp closed-source applications, their &lt;a href="https://lifehacker.com/stop-using-whatsapp-if-you-care-about-your-privacy-1825719172"&gt;problems with privacy and security&lt;/a&gt; are also well known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason attributable to this situation is lethargy and laziness - people just don't want to step into the shoes of power-users or even try and learn a new tool. And as for those power-users, they do occasionally experiment with freedom respecting software, but can't make a permanent switch because of compatibility - you can't convince your entire friend circle to switch to Jitsi and Mastodon overnight, can you? If you press too much, then they'll cut off the friendship and isolate you. And though you may end up with some freedom respecting messenger software, there will be no friends left to message if you go that route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward, freedom friendliness is going to be a very important attribute while choosing a software or even a hardware for us netizens, and the reason is the &lt;em&gt;ongoing concentration of technological power in the hands of a few&lt;/em&gt;. Its no secret that &lt;a href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2018/06/microsofts-github-acquisition-an-unbiased-perspective.html"&gt;large tech companies are eating smaller startups&lt;/a&gt; since last several years. If history is any evidence, this concentration doesn't result in a very healthy ecosystem. If we let only a few players like Microsoft, Apple, Google and Amazon to dominate the entire digital world, then we all know that the result is not going to be good, especially for us plebians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A healthy dose of competition should prevail in the ecosystem, only that can ensure that everybody thrives. We need more and more alternatives for Youtubes, Skypes, Facebooks and the Twitters of the world, and more importantly, people should start using them. However difficult it might be, stick with it for a while - search for popular plugins, raise bug reports on the project issue tracker, participate in user forums, contact the developers and your local open source meetups, walk that extra mile and you'll find that you've got more than a solution to your problem!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, our freedom is in our hands as a community or collective bunch of people. Its up to us whether we take control back into our own hands or let the technological powers dominate us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Open Source"></category></entry><entry><title>Smyte is no more - The latest episode in the acquisition saga of Tech Giants</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2018/06/smyte-the-latest-victim-in-the-acquisition-saga-of-tech-giants.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-22T20:25:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-06-22T20:25:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2018-06-22:/blog/2018/06/smyte-the-latest-victim-in-the-acquisition-saga-of-tech-giants.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not even a month has been passed since Microsoft gave a big surprise to the world at large and the open source community by &lt;a href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2018/06/microsofts-github-acquisition-an-unbiased-perspective.html"&gt;acquiring Github Inc.&lt;/a&gt; a few days ago, and there has been &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/06/21/twitter-acquires-anti-abuse-technology-provider-smyte/"&gt;another acquisition&lt;/a&gt; yesterday. This time, Twitter Inc. bought the well known online service &lt;a href="https://smyte.com/"&gt;Smyte&lt;/a&gt;. Smyte …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not even a month has been passed since Microsoft gave a big surprise to the world at large and the open source community by &lt;a href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2018/06/microsofts-github-acquisition-an-unbiased-perspective.html"&gt;acquiring Github Inc.&lt;/a&gt; a few days ago, and there has been &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/06/21/twitter-acquires-anti-abuse-technology-provider-smyte/"&gt;another acquisition&lt;/a&gt; yesterday. This time, Twitter Inc. bought the well known online service &lt;a href="https://smyte.com/"&gt;Smyte&lt;/a&gt;. Smyte was an online provider of anti-abuse technology services, i.e. things like AI algorithms for identifying online trolling, etc. Many customers were totally dependent on this provider's API which suddenly disappeared off the radar after Twitter Inc. acquired them yesterday.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A whole lot of customers and other depending services were affected because of this &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/seldo/status/1009873821141118976?s=09"&gt;including npm&lt;/a&gt;, the popular Node.js package manager. As usual, &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/sysadmin/comments/8swr1e/reminder_that_external_dependencies_can_shut_down/"&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; was one of the first places where people turned up to know what's going on and update their statuses. As one of the comments quite intelligently notes, this is a very good lesson on this modern web development way that involves depending on a zillion external services and leaving your application open to the whims of acquisitions and centralization of technology powers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;::: {.reddit-embed data-embed-media="www.redditmedia.com" data-embed-parent="false" data-embed-live="true" data-embed-uuid="5bebab31-c06c-4d2c-bbd0-d938f9f97409" data-embed-created="2018-06-22T14:47:54.034Z"}
&lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/sysadmin/comments/8swr1e/reminder_that_external_dependencies_can_shut_down/e13j9tx/"&gt;Comment&lt;/a&gt; from discussion &lt;a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/sysadmin/comments/8swr1e/reminder_that_external_dependencies_can_shut_down/"&gt;Reminder that external dependencies can shut down without notice&lt;/a&gt;.
:::&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://www.redditstatic.com/comment-embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Twitter was also filled today with tweets of complains from existing Smyte customers who have suddenly stopped receiving any communication from their service provider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/arthens/status/1009925187364458496&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Ashkenas, the inventor of famous Backbone.js and Underscore.js JavaScript libraries expressed his feelings in a very sarcastic tweet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://twitter.com/jashkenas/status/1010014139320680449&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know what was Twitter's intention before acquiring Smyte, but the way this is going on, this has to end in only one of the two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Either developers take lessons from these incidents and stop depending so much on layer-2 solutions and external dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Technology giants become a bit more empathetic to the needs of smaller businesses and understand that just acquiring other services isn't a solution to the innovation problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Open Source"></category><category term="Twitter"></category></entry><entry><title>It's high time we find alternatives to centralized platforms like Youtube, Patreon and Twitter</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2018/01/its-high-time-we-find-alt-to-centralized-platforms-like-youtube-patreon-and-twitter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-27T07:39:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-01-27T07:39:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2018-01-27:/blog/2018/01/its-high-time-we-find-alt-to-centralized-platforms-like-youtube-patreon-and-twitter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The other day, I was listening to this &lt;a href="http://www.jupiterbroadcasting.com/120622/peer-pressure-lup-227/#comments"&gt;Linux Unplugged podcast&lt;/a&gt; when I realized to what extent we have been locked in by the so-called "platforms" already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only few days ago, Google started blocking some of Amazon's videos on Youtube only because Amazon refused to sell Nest Cams and Chromecasts …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The other day, I was listening to this &lt;a href="http://www.jupiterbroadcasting.com/120622/peer-pressure-lup-227/#comments"&gt;Linux Unplugged podcast&lt;/a&gt; when I realized to what extent we have been locked in by the so-called "platforms" already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only few days ago, Google started blocking some of Amazon's videos on Youtube only because Amazon refused to sell Nest Cams and Chromecasts on their website among other things.&lt;!--more--&gt; Similarly, if you have been following &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/BryanLunduke/videos"&gt;Bryan Lunduke's Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; on Linux, you may have heard him complaining about Google trying to censor his monetization of any content that relates to "Linux".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, you may have heard stories about Twitter and Facebook too about how they sometimes actively try to censor content that doesn't match up to their political agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all these cases, it's the common individual who is made to suffer. In the good old days of 1990s, it was Microsoft who used to give a tough time to open source and libre folks using things like Internet Explorer and OEM deals to stop Linux, but these days, that role has been taken over by these platforms who are slowly trying to become walled gardens in their own rights, to which they can control access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the famous saying goes, "Power corrupts and absolute power corrupts absolutely". If we let these platforms continue their monopolies, it won't take long for them to do more sinister things that will hamper free speech and people's freedom. As free-thinking individuals, it's our duty to find, use and support open source alternatives to these platforms. Of course, there are many open source projects who are helping us with that, all we have to do is support them in whatever way we we can. But at the very least, we can start by using these services:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Open Source Twitter Replacement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://joinmastodon.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mastodon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Mastodon is a decentralized version of Twitter. Which means that unlike Twitter (which has a single platform called Twitter.com), Mastodon is decentralized across multiple nodes, you can join any of them (or even start your own!). All nodes are federated of course, which means irrespective of which node you sign up on, you can see all the content, and connect with anybody on the Mastodon network. You can give it a try by signing up on &lt;a href="https://mastodon.social/"&gt;Mastodon.social&lt;/a&gt;, a popular node that I've been using since quite a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://matrix.org/"&gt;Matrix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Matrix is an "open network for decentralized communication". Though I haven't used it personally, it seems to be a decentralized social platform along similar lines as Mastodon (Let me know in comments if you've used it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A distinct advantage of decentralized platforms like Mastodon and Matrix is that there is no giant corporation to censor your free speech, or collect private data on you. The decentralized nodes are run by people like you and me, so they are like the Linux who is standing up against all the walled platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Open Source Patreon Replacement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.liberapay.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liberapay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Liberapay is a freedom friendly implementation which can act as a replacement for Patreon, a popular platform for open source contributors to get donations from their patrons. Patreon has been behaving quite odd lately (increase in transaction fees, network problems, etc.), hence Liberapay deserves a mention as an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.dash.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dash&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Dash is a crypto currency platform that might also help in switching over from Patreon. It's built along similar lines to the Bitcoin, but has two mining layers instead of one. Using the Dash platform isn't necessarily important, the point here is that a crypto currency can be used instead of regular ways of funding for open source projects, alternatives like Bitcoin, Litecoin, etc. can also be used of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Open Source YouTube Replacement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Chocobozzz/PeerTube"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PeerTube&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; PeerTube uses &lt;a href="https://github.com/webtorrent/webtorrent"&gt;WebTorrent&lt;/a&gt;, a JavaScript (browser accessible) version of the Bittorrent client to make peer-to-peer video streaming possible using the Bittorrent protocol. In other words, it is an "open platform" version of YouTube, a chance to escape its walled garden.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Twitter"></category><category term="Youtube"></category><category term="Open Source"></category></entry><entry><title>The Reviewer's Duty and the Tragedy of the commons</title><link href="https://prahladyeri.github.io/blog/2017/08/reviewers-duty-and-tragedy-of-commons.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-31T04:21:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-08-31T04:21:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Prahlad Yeri</name></author><id>tag:prahladyeri.github.io,2017-08-31:/blog/2017/08/reviewers-duty-and-tragedy-of-commons.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Economics, there is a concept called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tragedy_of_the_commons"&gt;Tragedy of the Commons&lt;/a&gt; which simplistically means that when left to their own mechanism, individuals acting out of their own self interest sometimes behave in a manner which is against the common interest of all.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Reviewer's Duty" src="/uploads/old/stock/finger-769300_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some popular examples of this are air and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Economics, there is a concept called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tragedy_of_the_commons"&gt;Tragedy of the Commons&lt;/a&gt; which simplistically means that when left to their own mechanism, individuals acting out of their own self interest sometimes behave in a manner which is against the common interest of all.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Reviewer's Duty" src="/uploads/old/stock/finger-769300_small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some popular examples of this are air and water pollution. Companies that manufacture chemicals or other substances don’t bother much about pollution as it isn’t in their immediate best interest, at least in the short term. But they fail to realize that in the long term, the pollution is going to affect them too along with the sustainability of every individual on earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for things like air and water pollution, there are regulatory bodies that keep a check on the polluters. Now, you might be wondering how on earth does the tragedy of commons have anything to do with internet reviews?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the 21st century where the entire world is moving towards a global village ideal, and its no secret that actions of one individual affect others too in the digital realm. For example, its popularly known in SEO circles that &lt;strong&gt;Links&lt;/strong&gt; are the very currency and life-blood on the Internet. If you link to someone on your website, you provide them lots of traffic by recommending to your own site visitors. Not only that, the number of incoming links to a url very much affects the search engine results for that url too. For e-commerce and other sites whose income depends directly on the incoming web traffic to an extent, a link refferal is very much akin to a boon, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar currency which is getting a lot of importance lately is &lt;strong&gt;online reviews&lt;/strong&gt;. Like links, reviews affect the e-commerce sites and businesses too, but they help even more towards the common good of all consumers of those businesses - both current and potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the good old 18th century, “word of mouth” publicity was the way reviews and reputations used to work. Life was simple and the most people had to know for making both ends meet was about the grocery shop next door, or the vegetable market near the village centre. Reviews and reputations were something implicit in such a localized market, nobody needed to ask for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “word of mouth” technique works even to this day upto a certain extent, but life is more complicated today with the oncoming of digital. All varieties of simple and complicated products are available on shopping portals and the only thing that can guide you with decision-making in this chaos is reviews. With e-commerce growth projected at around &lt;a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/379046/worldwide-retail-e-commerce-sales/"&gt;2.29 trillion USD&lt;/a&gt; by the end of this year alone, the importance of honest and sincere reviews become even more important, both for the digital and offline consumer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is a major problem with how the review system presently works. As I mentioned in the beginning, the economic concept of &lt;em&gt;common good&lt;/em&gt; applies here. Firstly, almost everyone goes an extra mile to write a negative review about a product, but they don’t bother to write a positive review as they are “too happy with the product to bother”. This results in a very skewed review pattern of a product. Its a well-known thing that some defects happen in almost all products, but the ratio is important: whether ten defects were found in ten products sold, or a thousand products sold makes a world of difference. But since most of our positive reviewers just didn’t mention that thing, we may never know the difference and hold both the products (with a handful of bad reviews) in equally bad light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a “happy user” of a good product, bothering to switch on your laptop and write a review might be a bit painful, but each time you receive a good product, just remember that it might have as well turned out to be bad. And it might have happened just because someone else didn’t bother to write a wonderful review about an even better option that you missed on the portal! So, remember that &lt;em&gt;common good&lt;/em&gt; and do your utmost duty as a good netizen: Get up and write an honest review of almost everything that you have ever purchased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And reviews aren’t just important for e-commerce sites, its important for offline world as well. When you visit a restaurant, hospital or even a grocery shop, its very easy to find that on Google and write a review about it. If you visit a hospital or clinic and observed a serious neglience while receiving a treatment, your review can potentially help save someone’s life. Don’t ever think that what difference is your lone review going to make, if each one thinks like that, then we as consumers will keep getting taken for rides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason for writing honest reviews for real consumers, is review manipulation and paid-reviews by many e-commerce sellers. The concept of paid reviews is no secret, many e-commerce sellers pay people to write fake reviews on amazon, google, etc. Taking the short-term profit route and ignoring the long-term consequences on common good, those poor folks write those incorrect reviews. The only way to thwart these manipulators is that each and every one of the &lt;em&gt;actual genuine consumer&lt;/em&gt; writes a review too. The handful of manipulated reviews will get lost in the ocean of genuine reviews, and paid reviews will stop happening for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t ever think that there are already thousands of good reviews on a product, why should I write another one. As I said, all these thousands are very much required to counteract the paid reviews. Think of reviews as votes that you cast in an election. How important it is to elect a good candidate for the common good of the people is something that you already know. So, the next time you feel lethargic or lazy to write a good review, remember the &lt;em&gt;common good&lt;/em&gt; which will cause your good karma to return back to you with 200% interest!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Business"></category><category term="Reviews"></category></entry></feed>